<rss xmlns:a10="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>Guilherme Ferreira blog</title><link>http://gsferreira.com/rss.xml</link><description>Guilherme Ferreira blog</description><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2020/07/speaking-at-a-virtual-conference/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2020/07/speaking-at-a-virtual-conference/</link><title>Speaking at a Virtual Conference</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I had the honour of having one of my talks selected to &lt;a href="https://ndcoslo.com"&gt;NDC Oslo 2020&lt;/a&gt;. I was looking forward to speaking at Oslo Spektrum for the first time. This has been a wish for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Coronavirus has destroyed those plans. NDC was converted into an Online Conference. With that, I was facing a new and different challenge: Virtual Conference Speaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you had the chance of speaking in a virtual conference, you know that it's not the same experience. Even if you are an experienced Speaker, you will find yourself with strange feelings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, my talk went really well. So, this post serves to share what I have done to prepare myself. If you will be speaking in a virtual conference, this may be useful to you. My goal here is to describe what I've done and what I've learned. Hope it can be helpful to you.&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2020-07-07T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had the honour of having one of my talks selected to &lt;a href="https://ndcoslo.com"&gt;NDC Oslo 2020&lt;/a&gt;. I was looking forward to speaking at Oslo Spektrum for the first time. This has been a wish for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Coronavirus has destroyed those plans. NDC was converted into an Online Conference. With that, I was facing a new and different challenge: Virtual Conference Speaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you had the chance of speaking in a virtual conference, you know that it's not the same experience. Even if you are an experienced Speaker, you will find yourself with strange feelings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, my talk went really well. So, this post serves to share what I have done to prepare myself. If you will be speaking in a virtual conference, this may be useful to you. My goal here is to describe what I've done and what I've learned. Hope it can be helpful to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Setup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, image is an important part, and I didn't want to seem sloppy or unprofessional. Having a good camera is a must, but there are other things to consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Camera&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought a &lt;a href="https://secure.logitech.com/en-gb/product/hd-pro-webcam-c920?crid=34"&gt;Logitech C920&lt;/a&gt;. The image improved when comparing to the laptop webcam. Besides that fact, I'm able to use a tripod to hold the camera and align it with my eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aligning the camera with your eyes is useful. You will be speaking to a camera, so it's good to have it in the correct position. Level it with your eyes. It will feel more natural to you and to those that are watching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Lighting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lighting is a small investment that makes a huge difference in the result. You can always use natural light. In my case, I bought a simple &lt;a href="https://www.aliexpress.com/item/33020816527.html"&gt;light ring from AliExpress&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don't have a green screen, you need to take care of your background. Having a lot of things happening in the background can be quite distracting. Remember that your goal is to get the attention of the audience. They are at home, on their computer, and they can easily be distracted when compared to a conference room. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn't want to give them another good reason for distraction by having shiny objects on the background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I tried to create a minimalist background with a small décor to have a better look and feel than a white wall. I also used a led strip that I had at home to have a backlight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/speaking-at-a-virtual-conference-background.jpg" alt="Background" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Microphone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A decent microphone is a must. Using the laptop microphone is terrible. &lt;a href="https://dylanbeattie.net/2020/05/12/microphones.html"&gt;Dylan Beatie crafted an excellent blog post&lt;/a&gt; that can help. There you can also see the difference between different microphones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, the microphone was a concern, especially because I live in a noisy place with a ton of traffic. It's impossible not to listen to background noise in my house. So, I decided to invest in a USB Dynamic Microphone (&lt;a href="http://www.samsontech.com/samson/products/microphones/usb-microphones/q2u/"&gt;SAMSON q2u&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I recommend you to find the quietest place you can and use a good microphone. At least, something other than your laptop microphone. If you don't have background noise, an inexpensive Condenser Microphone can improve your sound quality a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've found really good information about Microphones, Cameras and Lighting &lt;a href="https://mattstauffer.com/blog/setting-up-your-webcam-lights-and-audio-for-remote-work-podcasting-videos-and-streaming"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Glare on Glasses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you use glasses like me, Lighting and positioning can be quite difficult. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facing direct light or bright screens was reflecting everything on my glasses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Light and screen reflexes can be quite distracting and don't feel natural. To overcome it, I position my screens on a diagonal line and the light ring from top to bottom. Besides that, I reduced the brightness of my screens. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9NWAcK-wM80"&gt;This video&lt;/a&gt; was really helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Stand-up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By standing up, you will see that your voice will be clear and you will have a better posture. If not have a standing desk, improvise. I managed the same result by stacking up my kitchen table with my daughter´s playing table. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/speaking-at-a-virtual-conference-setup-macro.jpg" alt="Setup - Stand-up" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Preparing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rehearse&lt;/strong&gt; in the same environment and with the same setup that you will be using.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Record it and share it with your friends and colleagues. Ask for  &lt;a href="https://gsferreira.com/archive/2019/07/leading-improvement-through-honest-feedback/"&gt;honest feedback&lt;/a&gt;. Use the feedback to improve.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rehearse&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Make sure that you have a Plan B&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What if your computer fails?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Will you use a pointer? Do you have extra batteries?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rehearse&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rehearse&lt;/strong&gt; with the same software that you will be using in the day. Make yourself comfortable with it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. Rehearse written so many times isn't a mistake. Honestly, &lt;strong&gt;the most important thing that you can do is rehearse&lt;/strong&gt;. Rehearse in the same conditions. Over and over again. By doing that you will feel more comfortable speaking to a camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day has been really pleasant to me. After multiple hours of rehearsing, I have found that my muscle memory kicked in. I didn't have the chance to feel stressed. I was feeling prepared. It was showtime and I was enjoying it. Nevertheless, there are a few things that helped me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Dress-up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will signal to your brain that it's time to do important stuff. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Barefoot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barefoot or use socks. You will find yourself more relaxed. You will also make less background noise with your feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Shutdown your doorbell&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make the possible not to be interrupted. Delivery man ringing the doorbell, your partner walking by, your dog barking... Try to find a way to reduce the probability of something like that to happen. But, if it happens, embrace it. Play with it. Prepare a joke if you can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Hydrate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a glass of water nearby. Do not forget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Connect to the audience&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can't move around, so try to make your hands visible and use them to communicate. Use different tones of voice to keep people connected. Ask for feedback in the chat and try to keep an eye on the chat in case you are looking for a more interactive talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/speaking-at-a-virtual-conference-micro.jpg" alt="Setup - closeup" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always remember that those attending, are there because they want to learn from you. So enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2020/05/that-flag-argument-is-yelling-at-you/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2020/05/that-flag-argument-is-yelling-at-you/</link><title>That flag argument is yelling at you</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the code yells at you trying to warn you that something is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flag arguments are one of those cases. Adding a Boolean argument to condition the execution is an easy fix, but we are doing the wrong thing.&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2020-05-27T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the code yells at you trying to warn you that something is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flag arguments are one of those cases. Adding a Boolean argument to condition the execution is an easy fix, but we are doing the wrong thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By adding a flag argument to a function, it's clear that we are ignoring the Single Responsibility Principle. The code is yelling at us, trying to explain that. No doubt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's take a look. When a function has a flag argument, we will find something like this (or even worse) in the implementation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/that-flag-argument-is-yelling-at-you-flag-argument.png" alt="Flag Argument" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wouldn't be better to have something like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/that-flag-argument-is-yelling-at-you-refactor.png" alt="Flag Argument Refactor" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When writing code, remember that the goal is to simplify our client's life.&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2020/05/dont-comment-what-your-code-is-doing-comment-the-why/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2020/05/dont-comment-what-your-code-is-doing-comment-the-why/</link><title>Don't comment what your code is doing, comment the Why</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Code comments are a common topic of love/hate discussions. 
It's particularly interesting to see developers shifting opinion while experience grows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Code Comments are a good idea because we are writing them down to help others. Even to help the future self.
But we use a lot of comments that don't help. This explains the Comments bad reputation nowadays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what can we do to improve our comments?&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2020-05-21T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Code comments are a common topic of love/hate discussions. 
It's particularly interesting to see developers shifting opinion while experience grows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Code Comments are a good idea because we are writing them down to help others. Even to help the future self.
But we use a lot of comments that don't help. This explains the Comments bad reputation nowadays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what can we do to improve our comments?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use a simple rule: &lt;strong&gt;Explain the Why, not the What.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see a lot of Comments that are explaining what the code is doing. That doesn't help. 
The effort that we put to write a Comment must be invested refactoring the code (&lt;a href="https://gsferreira.com/archive/2019/10/a-simple-tip-to-improve-your-code-maintainability-decompose-if-statements-into-methods"&gt;this is a good starting point&lt;/a&gt;). 
&lt;strong&gt;When we need to describe the What is because the code isn't readable at all.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's also pretty common to have obvious Comments. All we have seen that &lt;em&gt;"// Get a Customer"&lt;/em&gt; comment in a &lt;em&gt;"GetCustomer"&lt;/em&gt; method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="width:100%;height:0;padding-bottom:100%;position:relative;"&gt;&lt;iframe src="https://giphy.com/embed/gF8vDz0XAUfIWx9jUW" width="100%" height="100%" style="position:absolute" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://giphy.com/gifs/memecandy-gF8vDz0XAUfIWx9jUW"&gt;via GIPHY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those comments don't bring value. They raise the cognitive load required to read and maintain the code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the idea is to &lt;strong&gt;let the code speak for himself&lt;/strong&gt;. We only write comments, when we need to explain Why we have done something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's useful to understand why a piece of code was written in a certain way. 
Those Why comments can help us out to understand that there's a particular corner case, or the reason for the followed approach, or that, because of a bug (Link the bug from the comment), we need to do that. 
Those are a few examples, but you get the point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our code must be self-describing, but sometimes, we need to explain the Why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And remember: &lt;strong&gt;don't Comment the code that you don't need anymore. Throw it away.&lt;/strong&gt; In case you need it, it will be at the source control.&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2020/05/manage-your-code-as-a-successful-restaurant/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2020/05/manage-your-code-as-a-successful-restaurant/</link><title>Manage your code as a successful restaurant</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever noticed that a successful restaurant has a shorter menu? Especially when compared to those who are struggling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why?! &lt;strong&gt;Simplicity!&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you keep things simple, you focus on fewer things. You give your best and you can focus your effort. You can try to improve and perfect all details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, when life doesn't work as we expect, we start throwing new dishes into the menu. Expecting to please everyone. &lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2020-05-14T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Have you ever noticed that a successful restaurant has a shorter menu? Especially when compared to those who are struggling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why?! &lt;strong&gt;Simplicity!&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you keep things simple, you focus on fewer things. You give your best and you can focus your effort. You can try to improve and perfect all details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, when life doesn't work as we expect, we start throwing new dishes into the menu. Expecting to please everyone. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/manage-your-code-as-a-successful-restaurant-complex-menu.jpeg" alt="Complex menu" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spoiler alert: When you build something to everyone, you build it to nobody.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn't just the restaurants' reality. We see that in software too. When trying to convince new customers, throwing features into a product is usually the way to go. And it's hard to find a Product Owner who doesn't fight to have the team focused on new features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we should all be doing is to &lt;strong&gt;focus on what we have and what customers love.&lt;/strong&gt; Those features have a margin to improve. &lt;strong&gt;Don't bring a new feature into the product just because a customer needs it. Bring it because is inevitable.&lt;/strong&gt; Because it's obvious that your software will be so much better. Because you believe that you are in an especial condition and nobody can do it better than you. And don't forget to throw away stuff that doesn't "spark joy". &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src="https://giphy.com/embed/hvRoo3YcAPUheF3MxY" width="480" height="480" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can expand this concept to multiple software parts. High level, to a low level. Decompose the code in smaller objects or functions. Create focused "restaurants" specialized in one task. If you want Mexican food, you don't look for an Italian restaurant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Treat your code as a garden, which deserves care and dedication.&lt;/strong&gt; Don't write it and ignore it until a bug arises. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A chef who creates new dishes every single night will create a few stunning dishes for sure. But also, a vast number of massive failures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a continuous improvement mindset is what makes us better than the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2020/05/a-simple-way-to-build-your-javascript-tests-data/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2020/05/a-simple-way-to-build-your-javascript-tests-data/</link><title>A simple way to build your JavaScript tests data</title><description>&lt;p&gt;When writing Unit Tests, you will need to create test data objects for sure. Usually, those objects have tiny differences between different test cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There's a pattern that I especially like when I'm doing this is C#. &lt;a href="https://ardalis.com/improve-tests-with-the-builder-pattern-for-test-data"&gt;The Builder Pattern&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The builder pattern is an elegant solution to the problem and I really like it. But, is it a simple solution for JavaScript?&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2020-05-06T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When writing Unit Tests, you will need to create test data objects for sure. Usually, those objects have tiny differences between different test cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There's a pattern that I especially like when I'm doing this is C#. &lt;a href="https://ardalis.com/improve-tests-with-the-builder-pattern-for-test-data"&gt;The Builder Pattern&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The builder pattern is an elegant solution to the problem and I really like it. But, is it a simple solution for JavaScript?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's see how it would look like using the builder pattern in JS:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/a-simple-way-to-build-your-javascript-tests-data-builder.png" alt="Builder pattern" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, there's a lot of code needed to implement it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How can we do it more simply?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic idea is to &lt;strong&gt;use the &lt;a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Operators/Spread_syntax"&gt;Spread Operator&lt;/a&gt; to customize a default object&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's see how:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/a-simple-way-to-build-your-javascript-tests-data-spread.png" alt="Spread Operator" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2020/05/dont-declare-your-variables-at-the-top/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2020/05/dont-declare-your-variables-at-the-top/</link><title>Don't declare your Variables at the top</title><description>&lt;p&gt;When I start learning to code, I was taught to declare variables at the top of the code. I followed it for a long time before start questioning that absolute truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are writing code for others to read. So, we shouldn't present our characters too early in the story. &lt;a href="https://www.livescience.com/2493-mind-limit-4.html"&gt;Our working memory handle a strict number of things at a given time&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2020-05-04T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I start learning to code, I was taught to declare variables at the top of the code. I followed it for a long time before start questioning that absolute truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are writing code for others to read. So, we shouldn't present our characters too early in the story. &lt;a href="https://www.livescience.com/2493-mind-limit-4.html"&gt;Our working memory handle a strict number of things at a given time&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/dont-declare-your-variables-at-the-top-memory-overflow.png" alt="Working memory overflow" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping related concepts closer, we are reducing the cognitive load. This will lead us to clean and simple code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find evidence of that, in Design Principles. By using the &lt;a href="https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/laws-of-proximity-uniform-connectedness-and-continuation-gestalt-principles-2"&gt;Proximity principle&lt;/a&gt;, we form groups by keeping things closer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the reasons why &lt;strong&gt;I run away from global variables.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides the cognitive load reduction, there's a positive side effect from following this. &lt;strong&gt;I use this as a warning sign to extract a function. Whenever you can't keep the variables close to where they are used and to the top, extract it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, instead of doing this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/dont-declare-your-variables-at-the-top-example1.png" alt="Example 1" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can do this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/dont-declare-your-variables-at-the-top-example2.png" alt="Example 2" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then refactor to this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/dont-declare-your-variables-at-the-top-example3.png" alt="Example 3" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2020/04/windbg-a-net-core-31-app-memory-leak/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2020/04/windbg-a-net-core-31-app-memory-leak/</link><title>windbg a .net core 3.1 app memory leak</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I've spent the past few days trying to fix a memory leak. I was having problems to figure out what was leaking, so I used windbg wishing that it would help me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess that I'm not an experienced user of windbg, so I google how to catch memory issues using windbg. There's a ton of information out there. The problem is that I didn't found a guide on how to do it with a .net core application.&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Tue, 14 Apr 2020 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2020-04-14T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've spent the past few days trying to fix a memory leak. I was having problems to figure out what was leaking, so I used windbg wishing that it would help me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess that I'm not an experienced user of windbg, so I google how to catch memory issues using windbg. There's a ton of information out there. The problem is that I didn't found a guide on how to do it with a .net core application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I'm sharing here how I've done it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install windbg (&lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows-hardware/drivers/debugger/debugger-download-tools"&gt;see here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add windbg.exe (x64 version) to your environment path.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install SOS (&lt;a href="https://github.com/dotnet/diagnostics#installing-sos"&gt;see here&lt;/a&gt;): &lt;code&gt;dotnet tool install -g dotnet-sos&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set breakpoint(s) using &lt;code&gt;System.Diagnostics.Debugger.Break()&lt;/code&gt; in your source code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Update your project (*.csproj file) to Load Symbols: &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;DebugSymbols&amp;gt;true&amp;lt;/DebugSymbols&amp;gt;&amp;lt;DebugType&amp;gt;pdbonly&amp;lt;/DebugType&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build your project using Release configuration: &lt;code&gt;dotnet build -c Release&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Launch with WinDbg attached to your project: &lt;code&gt;windbg dotnet [YOUR DLL PATH].dll&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bret.codes/net-core-and-windbg/#loadsos"&gt;Load SOS&lt;/a&gt; using &lt;code&gt;.load C:\Users\[USERNAME]\.dotnet\sos\sos.dll .&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/windbg-a-net-core-31-app-memory-leak-load-sos.png" alt="windbg - load sos" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;code&gt;g&lt;/code&gt; to go to the first breakpoint.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enter &lt;code&gt;!gchandles&lt;/code&gt; to see garbage collector handles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;!DumpHeap /d -mt [MT]&lt;/code&gt; using the memory type id from the result list of the previous command. Example: &lt;code&gt;!DumpHeap /d -mt 00007ffb4c85ca98&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;!gcroot -all [ADDRESS]&lt;/code&gt; using the memory address form the result list of the previous command. Example: &lt;code&gt;!gcroot -all 0x0000023cd2e71510&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following this guide, you should have a clue of what is still in memory and where the object is in use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope this helps.&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2020/02/optimizing-react-render-3-things-that-i-wish-to-know-before/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2020/02/optimizing-react-render-3-things-that-i-wish-to-know-before/</link><title>Optimizing React Render - 3 things that I wish to know before</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/optimizing-react-render-3-things-that-i-wish-to-know-before.png" alt="Optimizing React Render - 3 things that I wish to know before" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience with &lt;a href="https://reactjs.org/"&gt;React&lt;/a&gt; has been awesome so far. My feeling is that I just needed to understand the basic concepts to be productive with React. The problem is that there are a few advanced concepts that I was missing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, the lack of knowledge manifested itself as performance issues. To fix them I needed to learn in the hard way. So, I'm sharing this here because if I can prevent you from suffering from it, I would be glad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I observed that the components of my application were rendering too many times, even when I did not need them to re-render. The following 3 recommendations are the main reasons for that to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2020 00:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2020-02-26T00:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/optimizing-react-render-3-things-that-i-wish-to-know-before.png" alt="Optimizing React Render - 3 things that I wish to know before" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience with &lt;a href="https://reactjs.org/"&gt;React&lt;/a&gt; has been awesome so far. My feeling is that I just needed to understand the basic concepts to be productive with React. The problem is that there are a few advanced concepts that I was missing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, the lack of knowledge manifested itself as performance issues. To fix them I needed to learn in the hard way. So, I'm sharing this here because if I can prevent you from suffering from it, I would be glad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I observed that the components of my application were rendering too many times, even when I did not need them to re-render. The following 3 recommendations are the main reasons for that to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;💡 1. Don't pass props with an object by reference&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you invoke a component and set a prop with a given object, the object will be passing by reference.&lt;/strong&gt; This can cause all kind of problems. I was facing two distinct problems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Despite I was lifting the state up, the child components have access to the same instance of the state.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When passing props by reference, you can receive the same object in the prevProps and nextProps for a componentShouldUpdate event. That will cause you problems. You want to compare those props to know what has been changed, but you are looking at the exact same object.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;✅ What to do?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use the spread operator. If you have a complex data structure, with multi-level deepness, use a tool like &lt;a href="https://lodash.com/docs/#cloneDeep"&gt;Lodash cloneDeep&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;💡 2. Only pass properties needed to the component&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make sure that you don't provide information that isn't needed to the child components. Try to only pass simple props with primitive types or functions.&lt;/strong&gt; If you pass a complex object and the child object only needs part of it, React will need to re-render the component. React will re-render every time that the props or the state change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;✅ What to do?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Review your components and question all those props where the prop type is Object or Any.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;💡 3. React Memo or Pure Components&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memo and Pure Components are an excellent way of improving performance. But, unless you are using them in the correct scenario you will not see the benefits. &lt;strong&gt;If you are providing a complex object&lt;/strong&gt; (like explained in recommendation 2) &lt;strong&gt;Memo and Pure Components will not work as you expect.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand that, you need to know that a Pure Component is different from a Component. Pure Components implement the &lt;em&gt;"shouldComponentUpdate"&lt;/em&gt; with a shallow prop and state comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;React documentation (&lt;a href="https://reactjs.org/docs/react-api.html#reactpurecomponent"&gt;see here&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"&lt;code&gt;React.PureComponent’s&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;shouldComponentUpdate()&lt;/code&gt; only shallowly compares the objects. If these contain complex data structures, it may produce false-negatives for deeper differences."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;✅ What to do?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try to follow the recommendation 2. If you need to have a complex data structure, use a Component and implement the &lt;em&gt;"shouldComponentUpdate"&lt;/em&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also take a look into react-fast-compare to help you out comparing complex data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, try to use primitive data as Props and use Pure Components or Memo when you can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can't, be sure that you clone the data and implement the &lt;em&gt;"shouldComponentUpdate"&lt;/em&gt; by yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that this helps you.&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2020/02/one-on-ones-using-behavioural-science-to-maximize-the-impact/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2020/02/one-on-ones-using-behavioural-science-to-maximize-the-impact/</link><title>One-on-ones - Using behavioural science to maximize the impact</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/one-on-ones-using-behavioural-science-to-maximize-the-impact.png" alt="One-on-ones - Using behavioural science to maximize the impact." /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you manage or mentor people, you should be doing one-on-one meetings. 
They are one of the most important tools that you have, so, it's important to maximize the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One-on-one meetings are an excellent moment for goal setting&lt;/strong&gt;. 
We tend to advise for improvement &lt;strong&gt;and it's a good practice to set a goal&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that those goals tend to have the same destiny of new year's eve goals and fail miserably (by the way, if your gym goal has made through January you are doing a good job!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we do one-on-one meetings we hope to improve people's lives and the difficult part isn't to identify those goals, those improvement opportunities. 
&lt;strong&gt;The difficult part is to help the team to achieve those goals.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, the intentions are good, and everyone is genuinely trying to do their best. 
I don't see these failures as people's fault, because we, as humans, are specialists in failing to achieve goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have been in this situation, probably you have noticed that goals use to stay in the "To do" state for a long time. 
So the question is: &lt;strong&gt;What can we do to be more effective?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 00:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2020-02-10T00:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/one-on-ones-using-behavioural-science-to-maximize-the-impact.png" alt="One-on-ones - Using behavioural science to maximize the impact." /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you manage or mentor people, you should be doing one-on-one meetings. 
They are one of the most important tools that you have, so, it's important to maximize the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One-on-one meetings are an excellent moment for goal setting&lt;/strong&gt;. 
We tend to advise for improvement &lt;strong&gt;and it's a good practice to set a goal&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that those goals tend to have the same destiny of new year's eve goals and fail miserably (by the way, if your gym goal has made through January you are doing a good job!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we do one-on-one meetings we hope to improve people's lives and the difficult part isn't to identify those goals, those improvement opportunities. 
&lt;strong&gt;The difficult part is to help the team to achieve those goals.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, the intentions are good, and everyone is genuinely trying to do their best. 
I don't see these failures as people's fault, because we, as humans, are specialists in failing to achieve goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have been in this situation, probably you have noticed that goals use to stay in the "To do" state for a long time. 
So the question is: &lt;strong&gt;What can we do to be more effective?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the answer is in &lt;strong&gt;Behavioural Science&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multiple studies already present how we should approach Goal Setting and what to do to achieve our goals. So, based on Behavioural Science, what do I recommend:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🎯 Specific Goals with a specific deadline.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;💡 Suggestion: Propose goals that are specific and easy measure. Assign a deadline. 
Remember not to impose goals. You are advising, so your role is mentorship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🎯 Create a simple plan with small steps.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;💡 Suggestion: Elaborate on the simplest plan possible. A complex plan is more likely to fail
Small steps are easy to measure and to see progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🎯 Try to form a new habit.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;💡 Suggestion: Goals are an excellent opportunity to form new habits. 
Make sure that you plan for routine small steps. 
By associating those steps to routine, the habit will be more likely to stick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Commit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🎯 Find someone that will act as a referee to enforce a penalty if he fails. If you don't find anyone, do it yourself.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;💡 Suggestion: Work with your colleague to find a referee and a good career mentor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🎯 Advice to make the goals public. This will raise the commitment level and help stick to it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;💡 Suggestion: Lead by example. Inform the team of your own goals. Write it down in a shared space (Slack, Whiteboard, Email, etc.). 
This way, everyone will feel safe to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Reward and Punish&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🎯 Make commitments that put something meaningful at stake and impose a non-negotiable rule. This way we work harder to achieve our goals.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;💡 Suggestion: Recommend to assume a goal and commit to a task that no one likes in case of failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Feedback&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🎯 Give feedback. Probably you are the reason for that goal, so you should give feedback on the progress or the lack of it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;💡 Suggestion: Keep frequent one-on-ones and always do a follow-up to the "active" goals.
Be honest and try to present data and examples to demonstrate your point of view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In your next one-on-one try to apply these. If you don't have one-on-ones, make that your first Goal.&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2019/12/start-thinking-inside-the-box/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2019/12/start-thinking-inside-the-box/</link><title>Start thinking inside the box</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/start-thinking-inside-the-box.png" alt="Don't you freeze when you are asked to be creative and think outside the box?" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don't you freeze when you are asked to be creative and think outside the box?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If so, you probably have been in the following places. Rumbling through ideas without consequences. Don't know where to start. Being repetitive. Procrastinating. Those are just a few consequences when we are facing a clean slate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These leads us to frustration, disappointment and lack of confidence in our creative skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably you even think: &lt;em&gt;"How the hell could Steve Jobs be so creative? That guy was a genius! He could think outside the box for sure."&lt;/em&gt; Well... I don't think so. Let's see why.&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2019 00:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2019-12-02T00:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/start-thinking-inside-the-box.png" alt="Don't you freeze when you are asked to be creative and think outside the box?" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don't you freeze when you are asked to be creative and think outside the box?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If so, you probably have been in the following places. Rumbling through ideas without consequences. Don't know where to start. Being repetitive. Procrastinating. Those are just a few consequences when we are facing a clean slate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These leads us to frustration, disappointment and lack of confidence in our creative skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably you even think: &lt;em&gt;"How the hell could Steve Jobs be so creative? That guy was a genius! He could think outside the box for sure."&lt;/em&gt; Well... I don't think so. Let's see why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2007, Steve presented to the world the first iPhone. A device that began the revolution of our daily companion: The Smartphone.  Today we can't live without it, but in 2001, we weren't so dependent for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;iPhone wasn't the first pocket computer that we carried. But, the iPhone was the first one to be really usable. A genius move of Steve Jobs was to understand the limitations of the current devices and drive the innovation to create delightful touch experience. Yes, kids, we used to need a keyboard or even a pen to work with our "smartphones".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stylus"&gt;&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/e8/HTC_Touch2_used_with_a_stylus.jpg/1280px-HTC_Touch2_used_with_a_stylus.jpg" alt="Phone Stylus" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The constraints were there, since the first day. iPhone was built on the shoulders of giants but the difference was to put together in the same device a plot of technologies, a good touch screen and a whole new experience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the &lt;strong&gt;constraints applied to the User Experience guided Steve to question what can be done to bring a better experience to life&lt;/strong&gt;. For sure, the fact of Steve being so obsessed with perfection was a constraint that forced the Apple team to find a new path, &lt;strong&gt;testing wild ideas&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If Apple had to start without constraints, they would need to forget the past, the Phone history.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything that has been accomplished in the &lt;strong&gt;past is for sure one of the most important guides in everything that we do.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Embrace the constraints and let them guide your creativity, because sometimes &lt;strong&gt;freedom, can be paralyzing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always remember, that when you were a little kid, you could bring to life an house, a car or even a plane with just two simple ingredients: A cardboard box and your imagination.&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item></channel></rss>