<rss xmlns:a10="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>Guilherme Ferreira blog</title><link>http://gsferreira.com/rss.xml</link><description>Guilherme Ferreira blog</description><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2020/02/one-on-ones-using-behavioural-science-to-maximize-the-impact/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2020/02/one-on-ones-using-behavioural-science-to-maximize-the-impact/</link><title>One-on-ones - Using behavioural science to maximize the impact</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/one-on-ones-using-behavioural-science-to-maximize-the-impact.png" alt="One-on-ones - Using behavioural science to maximize the impact." /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you manage or mentor people, you should be doing one-on-one meetings. 
They are one of the most important tools that you have, so, it's important to maximize the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One-on-one meetings are an excellent moment for goal setting&lt;/strong&gt;. 
We tend to advise for improvement &lt;strong&gt;and it's a good practice to set a goal&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that those goals tend to have the same destiny of new year's eve goals and fail miserably (by the way, if your gym goal has made through January you are doing a good job!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we do one-on-one meetings we hope to improve people's lives and the difficult part isn't to identify those goals, those improvement opportunities. 
&lt;strong&gt;The difficult part is to help the team to achieve those goals.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, the intentions are good, and everyone is genuinely trying to do their best. 
I don't see these failures as people's fault, because we, as humans, are specialists in failing to achieve goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have been in this situation, probably you have noticed that goals use to stay in the "To do" state for a long time. 
So the question is: &lt;strong&gt;What can we do to be more effective?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 00:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2020-02-10T00:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/one-on-ones-using-behavioural-science-to-maximize-the-impact.png" alt="One-on-ones - Using behavioural science to maximize the impact." /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you manage or mentor people, you should be doing one-on-one meetings. 
They are one of the most important tools that you have, so, it's important to maximize the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One-on-one meetings are an excellent moment for goal setting&lt;/strong&gt;. 
We tend to advise for improvement &lt;strong&gt;and it's a good practice to set a goal&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that those goals tend to have the same destiny of new year's eve goals and fail miserably (by the way, if your gym goal has made through January you are doing a good job!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we do one-on-one meetings we hope to improve people's lives and the difficult part isn't to identify those goals, those improvement opportunities. 
&lt;strong&gt;The difficult part is to help the team to achieve those goals.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, the intentions are good, and everyone is genuinely trying to do their best. 
I don't see these failures as people's fault, because we, as humans, are specialists in failing to achieve goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have been in this situation, probably you have noticed that goals use to stay in the "To do" state for a long time. 
So the question is: &lt;strong&gt;What can we do to be more effective?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the answer is in &lt;strong&gt;Behavioural Science&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multiple studies already present how we should approach Goal Setting and what to do to achieve our goals. So, based on Behavioural Science, what do I recommend:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🎯 Specific Goals with a specific deadline.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;💡 Suggestion: Propose goals that are specific and easy measure. Assign a deadline. 
Remember not to impose goals. You are advising, so your role is mentorship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🎯 Create a simple plan with small steps.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;💡 Suggestion: Elaborate on the simplest plan possible. A complex plan is more likely to fail
Small steps are easy to measure and to see progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🎯 Try to form a new habit.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;💡 Suggestion: Goals are an excellent opportunity to form new habits. 
Make sure that you plan for routine small steps. 
By associating those steps to routine, the habit will be more likely to stick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Commit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🎯 Find someone that will act as a referee to enforce a penalty if he fails. If you don't find anyone, do it yourself.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;💡 Suggestion: Work with your colleague to find a referee and a good career mentor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🎯 Advice to make the goals public. This will raise the commitment level and help stick to it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;💡 Suggestion: Lead by example. Inform the team of your own goals. Write it down in a shared space (Slack, Whiteboard, Email, etc.). 
This way, everyone will feel safe to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Reward and Punish&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🎯 Make commitments that put something meaningful at stake and impose a non-negotiable rule. This way we work harder to achieve our goals.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;💡 Suggestion: Recommend to assume a goal and commit to a task that no one likes in case of failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Feedback&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🎯 Give feedback. Probably you are the reason for that goal, so you should give feedback on the progress or the lack of it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;💡 Suggestion: Keep frequent one-on-ones and always do a follow-up to the "active" goals.
Be honest and try to present data and examples to demonstrate your point of view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In your next one-on-one try to apply these. If you don't have one-on-ones, make that your first Goal.&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2019/12/start-thinking-inside-the-box/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2019/12/start-thinking-inside-the-box/</link><title>Start thinking inside the box</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/start-thinking-inside-the-box.png" alt="Don't you freeze when you are asked to be creative and think outside the box?" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don't you freeze when you are asked to be creative and think outside the box?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If so, you probably have been in the following places. Rumbling through ideas without consequences. Don't know where to start. Being repetitive. Procrastinating. Those are just a few consequences when we are facing a clean slate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These leads us to frustration, disappointment and lack of confidence in our creative skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably you even think: &lt;em&gt;"How the hell could Steve Jobs be so creative? That guy was a genius! He could think outside the box for sure."&lt;/em&gt; Well... I don't think so. Let's see why.&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2019 00:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2019-12-02T00:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/start-thinking-inside-the-box.png" alt="Don't you freeze when you are asked to be creative and think outside the box?" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don't you freeze when you are asked to be creative and think outside the box?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If so, you probably have been in the following places. Rumbling through ideas without consequences. Don't know where to start. Being repetitive. Procrastinating. Those are just a few consequences when we are facing a clean slate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These leads us to frustration, disappointment and lack of confidence in our creative skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably you even think: &lt;em&gt;"How the hell could Steve Jobs be so creative? That guy was a genius! He could think outside the box for sure."&lt;/em&gt; Well... I don't think so. Let's see why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2007, Steve presented to the world the first iPhone. A device that began the revolution of our daily companion: The Smartphone.  Today we can't live without it, but in 2001, we weren't so dependent for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;iPhone wasn't the first pocket computer that we carried. But, the iPhone was the first one to be really usable. A genius move of Steve Jobs was to understand the limitations of the current devices and drive the innovation to create delightful touch experience. Yes, kids, we used to need a keyboard or even a pen to work with our "smartphones".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stylus"&gt;&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/e8/HTC_Touch2_used_with_a_stylus.jpg/1280px-HTC_Touch2_used_with_a_stylus.jpg" alt="Phone Stylus" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The constraints were there, since the first day. iPhone was built on the shoulders of giants but the difference was to put together in the same device a plot of technologies, a good touch screen and a whole new experience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the &lt;strong&gt;constraints applied to the User Experience guided Steve to question what can be done to bring a better experience to life&lt;/strong&gt;. For sure, the fact of Steve being so obsessed with perfection was a constraint that forced the Apple team to find a new path, &lt;strong&gt;testing wild ideas&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If Apple had to start without constraints, they would need to forget the past, the Phone history.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything that has been accomplished in the &lt;strong&gt;past is for sure one of the most important guides in everything that we do.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Embrace the constraints and let them guide your creativity, because sometimes &lt;strong&gt;freedom, can be paralyzing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always remember, that when you were a little kid, you could bring to life an house, a car or even a plane with just two simple ingredients: A cardboard box and your imagination.&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2019/10/a-simple-tip-to-improve-your-code-maintainability-decompose-if-statements-into-methods/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2019/10/a-simple-tip-to-improve-your-code-maintainability-decompose-if-statements-into-methods/</link><title>A simple tip to improve your code maintainability - Decompose IF statements into methods</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/a-simple-tip-to-improve-your-code-maintainability-decompose-if-statements-into-methods.png" alt="Extract method" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many times have you been in a situation where you can’t understand a small piece of code?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Readability has a huge impact on code maintenance because reading other’s people code (and sometimes even our code) can be challenging. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As developers, &lt;strong&gt;we tend to ignore the UX (user experience) of our code&lt;/strong&gt;. Every single line of code that we do, will eventually be used by others. Is important to be sure that we do the best possible job for our teammates and to future self.&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2019 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2019-10-23T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/a-simple-tip-to-improve-your-code-maintainability-decompose-if-statements-into-methods.png" alt="Extract method" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many times have you been in a situation where you can’t understand a small piece of code?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Readability has a huge impact on code maintenance because reading other’s people code (and sometimes even our code) can be challenging. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As developers, &lt;strong&gt;we tend to ignore the UX (user experience) of our code&lt;/strong&gt;. Every single line of code that we do, will eventually be used by others. Is important to be sure that we do the best possible job for our teammates and to future self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The worst code blocks in terms of UX are the ones that require a huge cognitive load.&lt;/strong&gt; It’s our job to ask our selves what we can do to reduce it and improve readability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually when I’m in a situation that requires high cognitive load to understand a piece of code, is because I face a huge and complex IF statement condition and I need to figure out what the hell it’s supposed to do. Do you know the feeling? Having to sketch a decision tree trying to figure out what is happening?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How to avoid it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most simple tricks that I do every day and I tend to advise everyone to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My rule of thumb is simple: &lt;strong&gt;In case of a multi-part condition, extract it to a method and name it accordingly.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see it in practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine that you have the following expression, that wants to validate if the customer can pay the Order with Credit Card. To do that, the customer should have an active Credit Card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;if (order.PayWithCreditCard &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (order.Customer.CreditCard == null || order.Customer.CreditCard.ExpirationDate &amp;lt; DateTime.Today))
    throw new CreditCardPaymentException("Customer doesn't have a valid Credit Card");
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To improve it, you can extract the boolean logic related to the credit card validation to a static method, and name it with something easy to understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;public static void ProcessOrder(Order order)
{
    if (order.PayWithCreditCard &amp;amp;&amp;amp; IsCustomerCreditCardInvalid(order.Customer))
        throw new CreditCardPaymentException("Customer doesn't have a valid Credit Card");

      (...)

}

private static bool IsCustomerCreditCardInvalid(Customer customer)
    =&amp;gt; customer.CreditCard == null || customer.CreditCard.ExpirationDate &amp;lt; DateTime.Today;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By doing this you are abstracting the reader’s mind from details. In case the reader needs to know the details, he can drill down to the details.&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2019/09/you-should-start-working-remotely-once-a-week/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2019/09/you-should-start-working-remotely-once-a-week/</link><title>You should start working remotely once a week</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/you-should-start-working-remotely-once-a-week-head.png" alt="Ready to work from home?" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you know the benefits of remote working? Do you doubt that it would work for you? Would you like to give it a try? Don’t know how to convince your boss or even how to start?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If so, I have something for you.&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2019 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2019-09-04T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/you-should-start-working-remotely-once-a-week-head.png" alt="Ready to work from home?" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you know the benefits of remote working? Do you doubt that it would work for you? Would you like to give it a try? Don’t know how to convince your boss or even how to start?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If so, I have something for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article is based on my experience of having the complete&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="https://omnialowcode.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;company&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;working remotely once a week for the past few months.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remote working&lt;/strong&gt; has been growing in the past few years but for some organizations &lt;strong&gt;can be a change difficult to accept.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are in an environment with resistance to Remote Working, the best way is to &lt;strong&gt;propose a small experiment.&lt;/strong&gt; The best way to prove a hypothesis is to test it following the scientific method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggest you present the case to the leadership presenting a few reasons (listed below) and proposing a small experience to prove them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;5 reasons:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.inc.com/scott-mautz/a-2-year-stanford-study-shows-astonishing-productivity-boost-of-working-from-home.html"&gt;Studies report&lt;/a&gt; that working from home has a &lt;strong&gt;huge impact on productivity&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s a benefit the company gives which can &lt;strong&gt;help to hire people&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It &lt;strong&gt;reduces costs&lt;/strong&gt; both for the company and employee.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leads to an &lt;strong&gt;improvement of the team communication&lt;/strong&gt; skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Happiness&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Studies report that people who worked remotely were &lt;strong&gt;less likely to leave the company&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Health improvements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Less time spent commuting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How to start&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After presenting a few reasons supporting your case, the best thing to do is to propose an experiment to evaluate the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start small.&lt;/strong&gt; I suggest starting with one day a week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set a period for the experiment.&lt;/strong&gt; I suggest to never do it for less than 3 months since in the first weeks everyone is still adapting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try to &lt;strong&gt;block a day in the calendar.&lt;/strong&gt; For example, schedule a recurring “Remote Wednesday” meeting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try to &lt;strong&gt;organize the work to leave remote days free of meetings.&lt;/strong&gt; If you have a creative job, this is a &lt;strong&gt;good day to focus&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure that everyone has a &lt;strong&gt;good pair of headphones&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure that the team has the &lt;strong&gt;right tools to facilitate the communication&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href="https://slack.com"&gt;Slack&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://teams.microsoft.com/start"&gt;Microsoft Teams&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.skype.com/"&gt;Skype&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/"&gt;Zoom&lt;/a&gt; or other).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t forget to &lt;strong&gt;define a few success metrics and define how you will evaluate them.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have other technique to start this journey, please share!&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2019/08/the-secret-to-know-yourself/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2019/08/the-secret-to-know-yourself/</link><title>The secret to know Yourself</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/the-secret-to-know-yourself-head.png" alt="Have you ever heard a recording of your voice" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever heard a recording of your voice? You don’t sound like that, am I right?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone has been in that situation, and that is strange, especially because we spend so much time with us. Even so, we sound like a poor imitation.&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2019 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2019-08-26T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/the-secret-to-know-yourself-head.png" alt="Have you ever heard a recording of your voice" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever heard a recording of your voice? You don’t sound like that, am I right?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone has been in that situation, and that is strange, especially because we spend so much time with us. Even so, we sound like a poor imitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s really common to listen to people that seem pretty sure that they know themself. We even find a lot of books about self-knowledge. The world seems to lead us to believe that we need to find ourselfs by meditation and introspection. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if I think that taking the time to reflect is important, I don’t think that is enough. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The vision that we have about us tend to be highly influenced by our ideals and our dreams.&lt;/strong&gt; Our brain is a specialist in fooling us and uses our wishes to trick us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what can we do to escape that illusion? We need to see how we act as if we were in an out-of-body experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can use professional sports as an example. We see athletes recording their training as a performance analysis tool. This is a good tool that top performances use to perfect their craft. &lt;strong&gt;Seeing yourself performing in a given context, can be enlightening.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can follow the example of pro-athletes and record yourself while performing a given task to try to figure out what to improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, the reality is that when we know that we are &lt;strong&gt;being observed, we start acting differently than we normally do and influence the outcome.&lt;/strong&gt; Similar to the Observer Paradox from quantum mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Observer paradox: the observer's paradox refers to a situation in which the phenomenon being observed is unwittingly influenced by the presence of the observer/investigator.&lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Observer%27s_paradox"&gt;wikipedia.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://factmyth.com/factoids/observing-a-phenomenon-affects-its-outcome/"&gt;factmyth.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t know this paradox, I highly recommend the following video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/DfPeprQ7oGc" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if recording yourself can be a good way to lie to yourself, what can you do!?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The secret is Feedback! Ask for feedback!&lt;/strong&gt; I’ve written an &lt;a href="http://gsferreira.com/archive/2019/07/leading-improvement-through-honest-feedback/"&gt;article that you can find here&lt;/a&gt; about the importance of feedback for improvement. Go ahead and read it. I will wait…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reaching out trust worth people that spend a lot of time with you is the easy path. When we are in our day-to-day life, lost in routines, we tend to express our true self and that has an impact on the people that surround us. So, if we do something positive or negative, if we have an annoying or peculiar characteristic, people tend to see it and label you with that specific trait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be uncomfortable, but, &lt;strong&gt;if you want to know who you are, you need to look inside, but you also need to look to the world and discover the impact that you have in others&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we end here, I want to challenge you to a quick challenge that can lead you into this self know journey. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write down 5 words that you think that describe yourself. 5 things that you think that reflects yourself and that other recall those words when thinking about you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find 5 people and ask them to send you 3 words that describe you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compare the results and see if something that you don’t expect to emerge from their feedback. Sometimes we have bad surprises, but I prefer to know and do something than keep doing the same.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go to your email and send a mail to 5 people that you trust them to give honest feedback. If you're looking to know yourself in a given context try to target people that are part of that given context. If you want to know “who am I as a leader?” reach out to your team and old team members. If you want to know “who am I as a friend?” reach out a group of friends important to you. If you want to know you in multiple contexts, just multiply the challenge. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you learn something new about yourself, please share!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next time you are in a one-on-one meeting, in an interview or in another context where you can have valuable feedback, don't forget to ask for feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2019/07/leading-improvement-through-honest-feedback/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2019/07/leading-improvement-through-honest-feedback/</link><title>Leading Improvement through Honest Feedback</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/leading-improvement-through-honest-feedback-head.png" alt="if it hurts, do it more often" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When was the last time that a waitress asked about your meal and you were really honest?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t feel ashamed. I’ve definitively been there. Saying that the meal was good when It was dry or too salty for your taste, is more common than we can think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, being honest when something is wrong isn’t something that we humans tend to feel comfortable about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably you are asking: why the hell should I be honest and risk to advancing into a difficult conversion?! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because &lt;strong&gt;the worst kind of feedback is fake feedback&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2019 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2019-07-15T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/leading-improvement-through-honest-feedback-head.png" alt="if it hurts, do it more often" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When was the last time that a waitress asked about your meal and you were really honest?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t feel ashamed. I’ve definitively been there. Saying that the meal was good when It was dry or too salty for your taste, is more common than we can think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, being honest when something is wrong isn’t something that we humans tend to feel comfortable about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably you are asking: why the hell should I be honest and risk to advancing into a difficult conversion?! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because &lt;strong&gt;the worst kind of feedback is fake feedback&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Leading improvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever thought that the restaurant could have done something to improve if you have been sincere? Wouldn’t you love to have customers telling you what you should do, to delight them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is that &lt;strong&gt;without the truth, we can’t improve.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Empty criticism and snark does no one any good. But genuine, useful, insightful feedback is a priceless gift.&lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;Seth Godin&lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://seths.blog/2014/01/the-feedback-youve-been-waiting-for/"&gt;https://seths.blog/2014/01/the-feedback-youve-been-waiting-for/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Promote feedback&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When you give good feedback, you are showing kindness&lt;/strong&gt;, even when it’s not positive feedback. They should see you as a Consultant that doesn’t send a bill. Next time that you aren’t sure if you should speak up, remember that in the end, they should thank you for the consideration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously that in a few cases you will find fences. Some people prefer to ignore and to resist, but in those cases, just move on. They won’t be in the business for too long for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To empower mutual constructive feedback, make sure you &lt;strong&gt;respond to honest feedback with a “Thank you”&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
If you don’t assume a defensive posture and you really look grateful, you will be encouraging the behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;It can be difficult&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DevOps community has a mantra with which I agree: “if it hurts, do it more often”. I believe that this applies to feedback also. 
It may be uncomfortable to start asking for honest feedback or even more to start giving feedback, especially when isn’t that good. But, if you do it over and over again, you will see that it will become natural and you will stop overthinking about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s really important not to be ashamed for pointing out negative things, because when you always give “OK answers”, your honest positive comments will not have an impact.
If you are known as the guy who speaks honestly, you will be taken into consideration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Make it easy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since feedback is so valuable, why do we tend to make so difficult for others to give us feedback?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably I want to tell you how I feel when I’m using your product, but at the moment when I understand that I need to create a user in a website and fill a 20 field long bug report, you can be sure that I will move on the next time I have an improvement idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, &lt;strong&gt;please bring to your systems a simple way to collect feedback&lt;/strong&gt;. Anyone should be able to leave you a note in 40 seconds and feel selfless, instead of 5 minutes of swearing and disappointment. 
If you are concerned that 40 seconds won’t be enough to capture all you need to know from the user, I bet that the user will be happier to answer an email with your questions afterward than upfront. At least they know that you have listened. No one wants to speak with a database, specially if nobody cares about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember that &lt;strong&gt;a good idea can arise anywhere at any time&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How to give honest feedback&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Being honest doesn’t mean being rudely honest.&lt;/strong&gt; No one wants to feel like being part of a Kitchen Nightmares episode, with Chef Gordon Ramsay yelling how incompetent we must be. That’s not fun. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are better ways to deliver feedback. I’ve 5 tips that you can start with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be humble.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Express your feedback as an opinion. For example, saying that the food is “Full of salt” is different than saying “Is too salty for my taste”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expose only your top 3 ideas. Don’t be too nitpicking. Having a “shopping list” of stuff won’t help.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Balance positive feedback with negative feedback. When we have something bad to say, we can easily forget to say good things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have an idea on how to improve, say it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://randomcrab.com/valuable-feedback/"&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/leading-improvement-through-honest-feedback-valuable-feedback.jpg" alt="Valuable Feedback" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wrapping up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We live in a society that seeks approval in social networks, and that thinks that a “Like” is a good kind of feedback. This causes an illusion about the impact we have on society. So, next time you see that a given person, service or product has a positive impact on you, don’t limit yourself to follow them on Facebook or Instagram. Go ahead and send them a message telling how was your experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you are providing a service or selling a product, make sure you make it easy to receive feedback and encourage your customer to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you ready to give it a try? I have a challenge for you. In the next 24 hours, make sure you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Send a message to one of your favorite services, telling them one thing that they can do that would improve your experience. Don’t forget to tell them to keep up with the good work. 😉&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Say thanks to someone that positively impacted your life and you know that you never told them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leave your honest feedback to this post bellow 😊&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2019/04/logging-grpc-requests-using-serilog/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2019/04/logging-grpc-requests-using-serilog/</link><title>Logging gRPC requests using Serilog</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Using a Middleware to log Api Requests in ASP.NET Core is a no brainer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have given a try to &lt;a href="https://grpc.io/"&gt;gRPC&lt;/a&gt;, probably you want to follow the same technique and you will wish that the experience was the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've faced this challenge, in order to log the requests to my RPC services and I've been looking for a solution where:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can use &lt;a href="https://serilog.net/"&gt;Serilog&lt;/a&gt; to log the requests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I know all the requests made to my services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I know how long each request takes to respond&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I know the response status&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can correlate each log entry using a Correlation ID&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description><pubDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2019 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2019-04-09T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Using a Middleware to log Api Requests in ASP.NET Core is a no brainer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have given a try to &lt;a href="https://grpc.io/"&gt;gRPC&lt;/a&gt;, probably you want to follow the same technique and you will wish that the experience was the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've faced this challenge, in order to log the requests to my RPC services and I've been looking for a solution where:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can use &lt;a href="https://serilog.net/"&gt;Serilog&lt;/a&gt; to log the requests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I know all the requests made to my services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I know how long each request takes to respond&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I know the response status&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can correlate each log entry using a Correlation ID&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To accomplish that in gRPC, I took advantage of an &lt;strong&gt;Interceptor&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using an interceptor, you can intercept the invocation of GRPC methods and intercept Unary calls (Request/Response) or Streaming communication. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this example, we will be using a &lt;strong&gt;Unary Interceptor&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This example has been done on top of gRPC HelloWorld sample in version 1.19.0&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Step 1: Install Serilog&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start by download the Sample code from gRPC. You can find the instructions &lt;a href="https://grpc.io/docs/quickstart/csharp.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Install in the GreeterServer the serilog package &lt;code&gt;Install-Package Serilog.Sinks.Console -Version 3.1.1&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm using the Console Sink for demonstration proposes. You can easily find tons of sinks like File, Seq, Application Insights, Datadog, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To enable Serilog, create the logger at the beginning of the GreeterServer &lt;em&gt;Main&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;public static void Main(string[] args)
    {
      Log.Logger = new LoggerConfiguration()
        .WriteTo.Console()
        .CreateLogger();
      (...)
    }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Step 2: Create the Interceptor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the GreeterServer project create the &lt;em&gt;RequestLoggerInterceptor&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;using Grpc.Core;
using Grpc.Core.Interceptors;
using Serilog;
using System.Diagnostics;
using System.Threading.Tasks;

namespace GreeterServer
{
  public class RequestLoggerInterceptor : Interceptor
  {
    private const string MessageTemplate =
      "{RequestMethod} responded {StatusCode} in {Elapsed:0.0000} ms";

    public override async Task&amp;lt;TResponse&amp;gt; UnaryServerHandler&amp;lt;TRequest, TResponse&amp;gt;(TRequest request, ServerCallContext context, UnaryServerMethod&amp;lt;TRequest, TResponse&amp;gt; continuation)
    {
      var sw = Stopwatch.StartNew();

      var response = await base.UnaryServerHandler(request, context, continuation);

      sw.Stop();
      Log.Logger.Information(MessageTemplate,
        context.Method,
        context.Status.StatusCode,
        sw.Elapsed.TotalMilliseconds);

      return response;
    }
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interceptor is just logging the Status Code for each request and the time used to complete the execution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Step 3: Apply interceptor to the service&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To take effect, you need to bind the interceptor to the Service you want. To do that, go to the &lt;em&gt;Program.cs&lt;/em&gt; and configure the Server service binding to use the interceptor for the Greeter service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;using Grpc.Core.Interceptors;
(...)
Server server = new Server
{
  Services = { Greeter.BindService(new GreeterImpl()).Intercept(new RequestLoggerInterceptor()) },
    Ports = { new ServerPort("localhost", Port, ServerCredentials.Insecure) }
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Intercept method is an extension method, so don't forget to use &lt;em&gt;Grpc.Core.Interceptors&lt;/em&gt; namespace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you run the samples now, you will see this as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/logging-grpc-requests-using-serilog-simple-log-line.png" alt="Log entry" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Step 4: Add Correlation ID&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have multiple services being part of the execution of a particular request, most probably you would take advantage of having a Correlation ID to track the execution of a given request in every service. If you don't have one, I highly recommend you to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this example, we will be sending the Correlation ID as an gRPC request header and change the Interceptor to add it to every log line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's start by add the Correlation ID header to the RPC request done by &lt;em&gt;GreeterClient&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var reply = client.SayHello(new HelloRequest { Name = user }, new Metadata()
{
  new Metadata.Entry("X-Correlation-Id", Guid.NewGuid().ToString())
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this example, I'm generating a Guid just for demo purposes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the interceptor, access to the Correlation ID and push it to Serilog as a property. In this way, every single log entry on that context will have the Correlation Id property available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;using Grpc.Core;
using Grpc.Core.Interceptors;
using Serilog;
using System;
using System.Diagnostics;
using System.Linq;
using System.Threading.Tasks;

namespace GreeterServer
{
  public class RequestLoggerInterceptor : Interceptor
  {
    private const string MessageTemplate =
      "{RequestMethod} responded {StatusCode} in {Elapsed:0.0000} ms";

    public override async Task&amp;lt;TResponse&amp;gt; UnaryServerHandler&amp;lt;TRequest, TResponse&amp;gt;(TRequest request,
      ServerCallContext context, UnaryServerMethod&amp;lt;TRequest, TResponse&amp;gt; continuation)
    {
      var sw = Stopwatch.StartNew();

      var correlationId = context.RequestHeaders
        .FirstOrDefault(h =&amp;gt; h.Key.Equals("X-Correlation-Id", StringComparison.OrdinalIgnoreCase))?.Value;
      using (Serilog.Context.LogContext.PushProperty("CorrelationID", correlationId))
      {
        var response = await base.UnaryServerHandler(request, context, continuation);

        sw.Stop();
        Log.Logger.Information(MessageTemplate,
          context.Method,
          context.Status.StatusCode,
          sw.Elapsed.TotalMilliseconds);

        return response;
      }
    }
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To complete the work, we need to configure Serilog to use the Properties pushed to the context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go back to the &lt;em&gt;GreeterServer Program&lt;/em&gt; and change the logger configuration to have a template where you use the Correlation ID and configure the log enrichment with the context properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Log.Logger = new LoggerConfiguration()
        .Enrich.FromLogContext()
        .WriteTo.Console(outputTemplate: "{Timestamp:yyyy-MM-dd HH:mm:ss.fff zzz} [{Level}] [{CorrelationID}] {Message}{NewLine}{Exception}")
        .CreateLogger();
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Step 5: Profit!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this tutorial, we created a simple gRPC interceptor. Now you have a request log with status codes and timings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/logging-grpc-requests-using-serilog-simple-log-line-with-correlation-id.png" alt="Log entry with Correlation ID" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go ahead and give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2018/06/versioning-net-core-applications-using-cake/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2018/06/versioning-net-core-applications-using-cake/</link><title>Versioning .net Core applications using Cake</title><description>&lt;p&gt;If you are moving to .net Core and you want to implement a versioning strategy in your application, now you have an awesome alternative to the good old fellow "AssemblyInfo". &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alternative is the &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/visualstudio/msbuild/customize-your-build"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Directory.build.props&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; file. If you place these file in the root folder that contains your source code, when MSBuild runs will add to every project the properties defined in the &lt;em&gt;Directory.build.props&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, we will see how to quickly setup a solution with multiple projects and use &lt;em&gt;Directory.build.props&lt;/em&gt; with &lt;a href="http://cakebuild.net"&gt;Cake&lt;/a&gt; to build and increment the version number.&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jun 2018 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2018-06-26T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you are moving to .net Core and you want to implement a versioning strategy in your application, now you have an awesome alternative to the good old fellow "AssemblyInfo". &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alternative is the &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/visualstudio/msbuild/customize-your-build"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Directory.build.props&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; file. If you place these file in the root folder that contains your source code, when MSBuild runs will add to every project the properties defined in the &lt;em&gt;Directory.build.props&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, we will see how to quickly setup a solution with multiple projects and use &lt;em&gt;Directory.build.props&lt;/em&gt; with &lt;a href="http://cakebuild.net"&gt;Cake&lt;/a&gt; to build and increment the version number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/versioning-a-net-core-applications-using-cake-directory-build-props.png" alt="Directory.build.props" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Setup your project&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's use the &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/core/tools/?tabs=netcore2x"&gt;.net Core CLI&lt;/a&gt; to quickly accomplish this task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start by creating a folder in your computer and then open the command line and go to the directory that you just created. Then execute the following commands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a Solution: &lt;code&gt;dotnet new sln --name DotNetCoreVersioning&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a console application and place it in the &lt;em&gt;src&lt;/em&gt; folder: &lt;code&gt;dotnet new console --name Application --output src\Application&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a class library and place it in the &lt;em&gt;src&lt;/em&gt; folder: &lt;code&gt;dotnet new classlib --name Library --output src\Library&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the console application to the solution: &lt;code&gt;dotnet sln add .\src\Application\Application.csproj&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the class library to the solution: &lt;code&gt;dotnet sln add .\src\Library\Library.csproj&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build it: &lt;code&gt;dotnet build&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you go to the folder you will see a solution file that you can open in Visual Studio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Adding the &lt;em&gt;Directory.build.props&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it's time to add the file that will do the magic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You just need to create a file with the name &lt;em&gt;Directory.build.props&lt;/em&gt; inside the &lt;em&gt;src&lt;/em&gt; folder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add it and then copy the following snippet into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;Project&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;PropertyGroup&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;Company&amp;gt;Empire&amp;lt;/Company&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;Version&amp;gt;1.0.1&amp;lt;/Version&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;AssemblyTitle&amp;gt;Death Star - Superlaser&amp;lt;/AssemblyTitle&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/PropertyGroup&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/Project&amp;gt;  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you run the &lt;code&gt;dotnet build&lt;/code&gt; command and go to the bin folder, of the console application or the class library, you can see in the DLL details that now the version is 1.0.1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Incrementing the version number.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this example, I will use a simple Cake script to increment the version number. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Setup your build script&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will explain how to do that manually, but if you are a &lt;a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/"&gt;Visual Studio Code&lt;/a&gt; user I highly recommend that you install the cake extension and use the tools provided by the extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Install the Cake bootstrapper. You can find &lt;a href="https://cakebuild.net/docs/tutorials/setting-up-a-new-project"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; how to do that. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create a &lt;em&gt;build.cake&lt;/em&gt; file next to the bootstrapper.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add the following snippet to the build.cake.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;///////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////
// ARGUMENTS
///////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////

var target = Argument("target", "Default");
var configuration = Argument("configuration", "Release");

///////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////
// TASKS
///////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////

Task("Version")
    .Does(() =&amp;gt; {

});

Task("Build")
    .IsDependentOn("Version")
    .Does(() =&amp;gt; {
        DotNetCoreBuild("./DotNetCoreVersioning.sln");
});

Task("Default")
    .IsDependentOn("Build");

RunTarget(target);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your build has now two steps and is building your solution using &lt;em&gt;DotNetCoreBuild&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Increment the version number&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To increment the version number we need to update the &lt;em&gt;Directory.build.props&lt;/em&gt; file. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the &lt;em&gt;props&lt;/em&gt; file is an XML we can use the Cake &lt;a href="https://cakebuild.net/dsl/xml/"&gt;XML aliases&lt;/a&gt; like XmlPeek and XmlPoke to read and update the version number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;I recommend you to use the Build Number of your build server to calculate the new version number. In this case, we will read the current version from the file content.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go ahead and copy the following snippet into the &lt;em&gt;Version&lt;/em&gt; task in your &lt;em&gt;build.cake&lt;/em&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var propsFile = "./Directory.build.props";
var readedVersion = XmlPeek(propsFile, "//Version");
var currentVersion = new Version(readedVersion);

var semVersion = new Version(currentVersion.Major, currentVersion.Minor, currentVersion.Build + 1);
var version = semVersion.ToString();

XmlPoke(propsFile, "//Version", version);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, we are reading the version property, incrementing the build number and then updating the &lt;em&gt;props&lt;/em&gt; file again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The result&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that our build script is completed, go ahead and run your Cake bootstrapper (&lt;em&gt;build.ps1&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;build.sh&lt;/em&gt;) and you will see that the compiled DLLs from all the projects have the version incremented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can use the &lt;em&gt;Directory.build.props&lt;/em&gt; to customize other project properties, not only for versioning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go ahead and give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2018/03/exploring-the-docker-container-metaphor/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2018/03/exploring-the-docker-container-metaphor/</link><title>Exploring the Docker Container metaphor</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post is my interpretation of the Container metaphor and how I use it to understand the concepts and explain containers to others.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Containers is one of the hot topics in the Software Development world and Docker is the technology that everyone wants to play with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to this hype, everyone has at least a brief idea of what a container is. The problem is that we can easily be confused about what containers really are and the advantages of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I faced the same problem and, in my case, explore the container metaphor helped me to understand it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;So, why containers?&lt;/h2&gt;

</description><pubDate>Mon, 05 Mar 2018 00:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2018-03-05T00:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post is my interpretation of the Container metaphor and how I use it to understand the concepts and explain containers to others.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Containers is one of the hot topics in the Software Development world and Docker is the technology that everyone wants to play with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to this hype, everyone has at least a brief idea of what a container is. The problem is that we can easily be confused about what containers really are and the advantages of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I faced the same problem and, in my case, explore the container metaphor helped me to understand it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;So, why containers?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you know, the Docker logo is a blue whale fully loaded with shipping containers, remembering us of a ship. The ship is a key part in this story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://docker.com/"&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/exploring-the-docker-container-metaphor-docker.png" alt="Docker" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine that you have a company in Europe and you want to transport your products to China by sea. So, you can find a ship with the adequate size and load the Ship with your cargo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Metaphor: In the software world, the ship is your Server.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a local trading association you find out that other companies are also sending products to China and you all can use a bigger Ship and send your products together to save some money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is: Should that big Ship carry the smaller boats?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/exploring-the-docker-container-metaphor-ship-of-ships.png" alt="Ship of Ships" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously not! No one would do that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Metaphor: Here, the big Ship is your server and the smaller ships are virtual machines. In this case, we have multiple Ships with all the capabilities to travel to China, but they are all constrained to the capacity and limitations of the big ship.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we have a big ship we load the ship with the cargo of every company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, you have to face a few challenges:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to be sure that the Cargo of a Port Wine company won't damage or contaminate the Cargo of other company?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to isolate the cargo?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to be sure that the cargo is inviolated?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to make sure that the cargo is being transported in the best conditions (correct temperature for instance)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, you can put the cargo into containers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Metaphor: In software, you are now loading the Server with containers. Containers will guarantee you that the software is isolated, protected and that a Container will take care what it needs, not the ship. Other benefit is that Containers are immutable so you can be pretty sure that your container won't be violated.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously you are now in a better situation then having a big Ship carry over small ships. But, &lt;strong&gt;don't forget that even an empty Container is pretty heavy&lt;/strong&gt;. Heavier then a few boxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Metaphor: This is a common misconception. The idea that a container is extremely lightweight is dangerous unless you are comparing it to Virtual Machines. In other case you are taking the risk of the other person think that containers are even lighter then running in the bare metal.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cool thing about Shipping Containers is that they are pretty standard and modular. You can assume that when the ship arrives in China, there will be a Truck that can transport it and that the container can return in a different ship. &lt;strong&gt;Shipping containers are ship agnostic.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Metaphor: That's another advantage of a container. Containers are pretty standard and without additional effort they can run in any Cloud or Server and be sure that they are self-sufficient.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/uBe2mknURG4"&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/exploring-the-docker-container-metaphor-containers.jpg" alt="Containers" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Composing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How could you be sure that you have two ships loaded in the same way? How to be able to say that they are "equal" in terms of cargo?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, since we can't 3D print a ship capable of transport this (at least in 2018), you will need to document the process. You need to explain how the ship is setup with all containers, explaining the position of each container, what is the cargo and how the multiple containers are interconnected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Metaphor: In Docker you use the Docker Compose to accomplish that. Compose is a command that uses a configuration file to know how to build multiple images and how they relate with each other.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Economic side&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is more expensive?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sending a big ship carrying small ships or containers?
&lt;em&gt;Metaphor: A Server with Virtual Machines or Docker Containers?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it better to load the cargo in a repeatable way, right? &lt;em&gt;Metaphor: Docker file and Docker compose are important tools to remove the uncertainty of new deployments.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wouldn't be nice to don't contaminate the cargo of one company because of a problem in other company products? &lt;em&gt;Metaphor: Isolation give you the confidence that your containers are protected. Containers are self-sufficient.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There's any concept that I'm missing in this interpertation? If so, go ahead and leave a comment!&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2018/01/json-patch-builder-online/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2018/01/json-patch-builder-online/</link><title>JSON Patch Builder Online</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Do you know the JSON Patch format? The &lt;a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6902"&gt;RFC6902&lt;/a&gt; defines the structure to express a list of operations to apply over a JSON Document.
This format is designed to be the payload of an HTTP PATCH method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The format isn't difficult, you can easily understand the rules and build it manually. But, I confess that sometimes I struggle with it, specially when I'm testing a PATCH to a complex object. 
So... &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://json-patch-builder-online.github.io/"&gt;I built a Tool to help me.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 00:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2018-01-08T00:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Do you know the JSON Patch format? The &lt;a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6902"&gt;RFC6902&lt;/a&gt; defines the structure to express a list of operations to apply over a JSON Document.
This format is designed to be the payload of an HTTP PATCH method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The format isn't difficult, you can easily understand the rules and build it manually. But, I confess that sometimes I struggle with it, specially when I'm testing a PATCH to a complex object. 
So... &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://json-patch-builder-online.github.io/"&gt;I built a Tool to help me.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/json-patch-builder-online.png" alt="JSON Patch Builder Online" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://json-patch-builder-online.github.io/"&gt;JSON Patch Builder Online&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is a simple and Open Source tool that you can use to calculate the JSON Patch needed to transform a resource/entity in the resource that you want. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To accomplish that, I used &lt;a href="https://github.com/Starcounter-Jack/JSON-Patch"&gt;JSON-Patch&lt;/a&gt;, a Javascript library, to calculate the Patch and &lt;a href="https://bulma.io/"&gt;BULMA CSS&lt;/a&gt; to have a good looking tool. 
I recommend that you go check them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have something that you want to see in the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://json-patch-builder-online.github.io/"&gt;JSON Patch Builder Online&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, feel free to open an &lt;a href="https://github.com/json-patch-builder-online/json-patch-builder-online.github.io/issues"&gt;Issue&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://github.com/json-patch-builder-online/json-patch-builder-online.github.io/"&gt;Contribute&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Links:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/json-patch-builder-online/json-patch-builder-online.github.io/"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://json-patch-builder-online.github.io/"&gt;JSON Patch Builder Online&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that this helps you.&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item></channel></rss>