<rss xmlns:a10="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>Guilherme Ferreira blog</title><link>http://gsferreira.com/rss.xml</link><description>Guilherme Ferreira blog</description><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2015/10/using-trello-to-manage-your-wine-cellar/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2015/10/using-trello-to-manage-your-wine-cellar/</link><title>Using Trello to manage your Wine Cellar</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Do you have a wine cellar at home?! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing too big, but the sufficient number of bottles to lose control?! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you really know what you have in your cellar?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post wants to help you solve those problems, and manage your home cellar with an amazing and free tool.&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2015 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2015-10-08T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Do you have a wine cellar at home?! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing too big, but the sufficient number of bottles to lose control?! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you really know what you have in your cellar?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post wants to help you solve those problems, and manage your home cellar with an amazing and free tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a good Portuguese, I have a small wine cellar at home, where I store the excellent wines that we produce at Portugal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/using-trello-to-manage-your-wine-cellar-cellar-1.jpg" alt="Wine botle" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don't have many wine bottles, but I struggled with some questions that I can't answer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I go to the supermarket, how do I know if I need to buy white or red wine?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to remember to buy a specific wine?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which are the oldest bottles?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to choose a bottle?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conclusion was simple, &lt;strong&gt;I need a system to manage it&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you probably know, I'm a huge fan of Trello and I trusted him to do the job.
If you don't know &lt;a href="https://trello.com/"&gt;Trello.com&lt;/a&gt; you have here a description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"&lt;a href="https://trello.com/"&gt;Trello.com&lt;/a&gt; is a collaboration tool that organizes your projects into boards. In one glance, Trello tells you what's being worked on, who's working on what, and where something is in a proces"&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How I did it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I brought some &lt;strong&gt;stickers, where I wrote letters&lt;/strong&gt; to name the columns &lt;strong&gt;and numbers&lt;/strong&gt; to stick in the rows. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I can organize the bottles with the combination, for instance A1, C6, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/using-trello-to-manage-your-wine-cellar-cellar-2.JPG" alt="Wine cellar" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I created a &lt;strong&gt;Trello board&lt;/strong&gt; for my wine cellar where I added &lt;strong&gt;4 lists&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To Buy:&lt;/strong&gt; Where I add a card for each bottle that I want/need to buy;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;White Wine:&lt;/strong&gt; The bottles of White Wine;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Red Wine:&lt;/strong&gt; The bottles of Red Wine;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Port Wine:&lt;/strong&gt; As a good Portuguese and as a Douro and Oporto lover, I have some bottles of Port Wine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can add more columns according to the Wine or another alcoholic drinks that you have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I created a &lt;strong&gt;card for each bottle&lt;/strong&gt;. I named the card &lt;strong&gt;with the bottle name and the slot&lt;/strong&gt; where I stored the wine. 
For example: "Kopke, Douro 2012 - E9" where "Kopke, Douro 2012" stands for the name and the region of the wine and "E9" stands for the slot where the bottle is.;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In each card you can also place a photo to identify the bottle if you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/using-trello-to-manage-your-wine-cellar-trello-1.png" alt="Board" /&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also like to categorize the wines with labels to add some metadata to help me choose a bottle when I need. 
For instance, you can create labels with price groups or a rating that you use to categorize the wine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/using-trello-to-manage-your-wine-cellar-trello-2.png" alt="Final result" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/using-trello-to-manage-your-wine-cellar-cellar-3.JPG" alt="Final result" /&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that this helps you.&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2015/09/7th-meeting-of-netponto-community-in-oporto/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2015/09/7th-meeting-of-netponto-community-in-oporto/</link><title>7th Meeting of NetPonto Community in Oporto</title><description>&lt;p&gt;We are bringing to Oporto the 7th Meeting of NetPonto Community.
The meeting will take place at Instituto Superior de Engenharia do Porto (ISEP) at 26 September 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Program&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;09:45    -  Check-in&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10:00    -  SOLR in .NET - Super Solid solution for a Super Fast Search - Pedro Neves Rosa &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12:00    -  The Future of Web Applications - ECMAScript vNext and others - Ricardo Brandão&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13:30    -  Closing Panel&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Thu, 17 Sep 2015 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2015-09-17T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are bringing to Oporto the 7th Meeting of NetPonto Community.
The meeting will take place at Instituto Superior de Engenharia do Porto (ISEP) at 26 September 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Program&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;09:45    -  Check-in&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10:00    -  SOLR in .NET - Super Solid solution for a Super Fast Search - Pedro Neves Rosa &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12:00    -  The Future of Web Applications - ECMAScript vNext and others - Ricardo Brandão&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13:30    -  Closing Panel&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Venue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instituto Superior de Engenharia do Porto (ISEP) - Room H202 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rua Dr. António Bernardino de Almeida, 431&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4200-072 Porto&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Portugal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.google.pt/maps/place/ISEP,+4200-072+Porto/@41.1778457,-8.6081006,17z/data=!4m2!3m1!1s0xd246449b419e1c1:0x16a6fd2fcace4efe"&gt;Map&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Registration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Registration: &lt;a href="https://netponto-porto-setembro-2015.eventbrite.co.uk/"&gt;https://netponto-porto-setembro-2015.eventbrite.co.uk/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2015/07/are-you-sure-that-android-is-better-than-windows-phone/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2015/07/are-you-sure-that-android-is-better-than-windows-phone/</link><title>Are you sure that Android is better than Windows Phone?</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SPOILER ALERT&lt;/strong&gt;: This text contains &lt;strong&gt;opinions&lt;/strong&gt; from the author about smartphones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Confession&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm a huge fan of Windows Phone since the early days and I have been using it since 2011. 
I followed the growing and I struggled with all the limitations in past years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until the last month I'd never used an Android Phone or an iPhone as my personal phones. 
I've been playing with them in work or with family phones, and I have to honestly say that I never fall in love for them. 
But I need to refer that I'm not a hater of them, I respect both Operating Systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can see their pros and cons and I try to stay away from those fanboy discussions &lt;em&gt;(usually I'm the guy that they will make fun because for my friends I'm the only person in the country with a Windows Phone)&lt;/em&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/are-you-sure-that-android-is-better-than-windows-phone-fun.jpg" alt="fun" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last month, I noticed that the camera button of my Nokia Lumia was a little loose and I decided that was time to send it to repair. 
I needed a substitution phone and I decided to give a try to Android because &lt;strong&gt;I'm a kind of disappointed with the Nokia hardware quality&lt;/strong&gt; and I was really &lt;strong&gt;curious to try a different operating system&lt;/strong&gt;. 
I've faced the experience with an open heart and really expecting to be surprised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed to get a Vodafone Prime 6, it's not a flagship product but it's a cool phone and I used it during a month.
Here I will explain &lt;strong&gt;what I loved in Android and what I missed from my Windows Phone&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*I want to point out that I won't compare hardware features.  *&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2015 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2015-07-22T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SPOILER ALERT&lt;/strong&gt;: This text contains &lt;strong&gt;opinions&lt;/strong&gt; from the author about smartphones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Confession&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm a huge fan of Windows Phone since the early days and I have been using it since 2011. 
I followed the growing and I struggled with all the limitations in past years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until the last month I'd never used an Android Phone or an iPhone as my personal phones. 
I've been playing with them in work or with family phones, and I have to honestly say that I never fall in love for them. 
But I need to refer that I'm not a hater of them, I respect both Operating Systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can see their pros and cons and I try to stay away from those fanboy discussions &lt;em&gt;(usually I'm the guy that they will make fun because for my friends I'm the only person in the country with a Windows Phone)&lt;/em&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/are-you-sure-that-android-is-better-than-windows-phone-fun.jpg" alt="fun" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last month, I noticed that the camera button of my Nokia Lumia was a little loose and I decided that was time to send it to repair. 
I needed a substitution phone and I decided to give a try to Android because &lt;strong&gt;I'm a kind of disappointed with the Nokia hardware quality&lt;/strong&gt; and I was really &lt;strong&gt;curious to try a different operating system&lt;/strong&gt;. 
I've faced the experience with an open heart and really expecting to be surprised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed to get a Vodafone Prime 6, it's not a flagship product but it's a cool phone and I used it during a month.
Here I will explain &lt;strong&gt;what I loved in Android and what I missed from my Windows Phone&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*I want to point out that I won't compare hardware features.  *&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/are-you-sure-that-android-is-better-than-windows-phone-oh-you-have-an-android-phone-tell-me-again-how-much-better-than-an-iphone-it-is.jpg" alt="better phone" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What I loved&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Meterial Design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love minimalist design and all the flat design stuff. I really like the work done by google. All the simplicity, the amazing use of the depth and animations made me like Material Design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Apps... Tons of Apps...&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you ask an Android fan how to do something he will reply to you "There's an App to do that!". This is a great resume of the main advantage of the platform comparing to Windows Phone.
I don't say that I like to 500 versions of angry birds or another useless apps in the Play Store, but I appreciate have the official version of some apps that I use every day like Trello, Pocket or Buffer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What I really don't like&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. User Experience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said before, I'm a huge fan of Material Design and I think that he can be an important tool to improve the &lt;strong&gt;experience&lt;/strong&gt;, but design isn't everything.
The applications have a lack of rules and patterns, even in the most popular apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more than once I had to think &lt;strong&gt;"Where should I touch?"&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;"What should I do?"&lt;/strong&gt; and those should be prohibited questions for a phone user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example: The following example shows three different cases where the main action button is in different places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/are-you-sure-that-android-is-better-than-windows-phone-ux.png" alt="Compair UX" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Opening notifications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Push notifications are amazing and I can't live without them anymore but in Android I got a little confused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most annoying thing in Android notification system is open a notification... double touch doesn't seems natural, at least for me.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Performance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I installed more a less 8 applications, all them popular (Trello, Sunrise, Pocket, Feedly...) and the phone is constantly blocking.
The system simply doesn't react in a fashion time. 
When a user touch to go to the main screen and nothing happens during 1 or 2 seconds the expirience is ruined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE&lt;/strong&gt;: I know that my Android phone isn't a powerfull machine, so I'm &lt;a href="http://smartphones.specout.com/compare/968-3120/Nokia-Lumia-630-vs-Vodafone-Smart-Prime-6"&gt;comparing him with the humble Nokia Lumia 630&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Updates&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I simply can't get it. I'm not able to figure out the updates that are available and how can I run them. 
Sometimes I got a notification to update the app "X", another times I need to go to Play Store to do it...
The most annoying thing was one day that I saw that he was installing updates using my 3G data connection without asking for a confirmation. :O&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What I missed from my Windows Phone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Tiles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isn't amazing to know your next appointment, see the twitter/facebook updates or read part of e-mail without a single gesture?
Windows Phone users know what I mean. Android users will probably say "There's an app to do that". :) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. People hub&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like the people hub and I missed so much the contact list navigation by the first letter.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/are-you-sure-that-android-is-better-than-windows-phone-wp-filter-contacts.png" alt="Navigation by letter" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Account management&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In android the accounts configuration is distributed and I'm a fan of that Windows Phone &lt;strong&gt;experience&lt;/strong&gt; where you buy a phone, go to the Email and Accounts settings, add your accounts and your phone is ready to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Vertical scroll at the applications list&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm not comfortable with the menu style of Android. Scroll horizontally between pages to get an application is not so productive as the Windows Phone vertical list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I use to say, Android is a "hackable" (customizable if you prefer the word) version of IOS. With Android we can have a phone that give us &lt;strong&gt;freedom to do what we want&lt;/strong&gt; and much cheaper than iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;strong&gt;won't say that Android is better or worst than Windows Phone&lt;/strong&gt;, because they both have a role to play in this game. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If to you the most important thing are Apps and be able to play the new Candy Crush or Flappy Birds since the first day, I recommend you to go to Android. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If to you, like to me, the most important thing is the &lt;strong&gt;experience&lt;/strong&gt;, so you should give a try to Windows Phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Users want apps and without apps you can't have users, but without users you will not have so many apps.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the near future, I will keep my Windows Phone. I know that there are rumors about the platform that aren't cheerful for WP users, but I really believe in the platform and I hope that Microsoft too.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to leave comments.&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2015/07/reduce-the-path-length-of-a-node-js-project/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2015/07/reduce-the-path-length-of-a-node-js-project/</link><title>Reduce the path length of a Node.js project</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you fighting with the path length of your Node.js projects? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are using Microsoft Visual Studio to development, I bet you do. If you don't, you will (this isn't any curse that I'm throwing at you)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Windows has the "Maximum Path Length Limitation" that is terrible for Node.JS projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"The specified path, file name, or both are too long. The fully qualified file name must be less than 260 characters, and the directory name must be less than 248 characters."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you know, when you install a package in Node.js, the npm will place the dependencies under the package folder. This process is recursive for each package, so you can easily overcome the path length.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there's no silver bullet to fix it (I'm not a Node.js guru, so please let me know if I'm wrong), but we can follow some tips to deal with it.&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2015 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2015-07-08T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Are you fighting with the path length of your Node.js projects? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are using Microsoft Visual Studio to development, I bet you do. If you don't, you will (this isn't any curse that I'm throwing at you)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Windows has the "Maximum Path Length Limitation" that is terrible for Node.JS projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"The specified path, file name, or both are too long. The fully qualified file name must be less than 260 characters, and the directory name must be less than 248 characters."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you know, when you install a package in Node.js, the npm will place the dependencies under the package folder. This process is recursive for each package, so you can easily overcome the path length.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there's no silver bullet to fix it (I'm not a Node.js guru, so please let me know if I'm wrong), but we can follow some tips to deal with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/reduce-the-path-length-of-your-node-js-project-dependencies-dependencies-everywhere.jpg" alt="dependencies everywhere" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;1. Azure Cloud Services - Change the output directory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are getting an error when you publish your cloud service to azure, it's probably because the deployment will place the output into a subfolder.
I've already had &lt;a href="http://gsferreira.com/archive/2014/11/azure-deploy-and-the-path-length-limitation/"&gt;blogged how to deal with it and you can find it here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;2. Find the packages that are leading you into the limit and install them&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine that you install a package that has a dependency from &lt;em&gt;request&lt;/em&gt; and that dependency made you overcome the path limit.
Go to the npm and install the package explicitly. Now, Node.js will not install the request in a subfolder of your first package.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;npm install request --save
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;3. Remove dev packages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Install the packages with the &lt;em&gt;"--production"&lt;/em&gt; flag to remove all development only packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;npm install --production
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;4. Remove duplicated packages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Npm has a command that will find for you the duplicated dependencies and install them as top dependencies.
With a simple command you can simplify your dependency tree and reduce your project size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;npm dedupe 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope this helps. Feel free to leave comments and ask questions.&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2015/06/6th-meeting-of-netponto-community-in-oporto/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2015/06/6th-meeting-of-netponto-community-in-oporto/</link><title>6th Meeting of NetPonto Community in Oporto</title><description>&lt;p&gt;We are bringing to Oporto the 6th Meeting of NetPonto Community.
The meeting will take place at Instituto Superior de Engenharia do Porto (ISEP) at 11 July 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Program&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;09:45    -  Check-in&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10:00    -  ASP.NET VNext, now in Mac! - Bruno Lopes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12:00    -  Building applications with Xamarin Forms - Rui Marinho&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13:30    -  Closing Panel&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2015 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2015-06-28T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are bringing to Oporto the 6th Meeting of NetPonto Community.
The meeting will take place at Instituto Superior de Engenharia do Porto (ISEP) at 11 July 2015. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Program&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;09:45    -  Check-in&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10:00    -  ASP.NET VNext, now in Mac! - Bruno Lopes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12:00    -  Building applications with Xamarin Forms - Rui Marinho&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13:30    -  Closing Panel&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Venue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instituto Superior de Engenharia do Porto (ISEP) - Room H202 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rua Dr. António Bernardino de Almeida, 431&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4200-072 Porto&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Portugal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.google.pt/maps/place/ISEP,+4200-072+Porto/@41.1778457,-8.6081006,17z/data=!4m2!3m1!1s0xd246449b419e1c1:0x16a6fd2fcace4efe"&gt;Map&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Registration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Registration: &lt;a href="https://netponto-porto-julho-2015.eventbrite.co.uk/"&gt;https://netponto-porto-julho-2015.eventbrite.co.uk/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2015/06/create-an-api-in-azure-app-service-revista-programar-n49/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2015/06/create-an-api-in-azure-app-service-revista-programar-n49/</link><title>Create an API in Azure App Service - Revista PROGRAMAR Nº 49</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I had the pleasure of write an &lt;a href="http://www.revista-programar.info/artigos/criar-uma-api-no-azure-app-sevice/"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; to the &lt;a href="http://www.revista-programar.info/anuncios/revista-programar-no-49-junho-2015/"&gt;Revista PROGRAMAR&lt;/a&gt;, a Portuguese collaborative magazine about programming. I’m glad with my first article for a magazine and especially because, I'm side by side with people that I admire like &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/PauloMorgado"&gt;Paulo Morgado&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/saramgsilva"&gt;Sara Silva&lt;/a&gt;, for instance. This was an amazing experience and I want to share with you the result of it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March, Microsoft announced an improvement in his services by introducing the new Azure App Service. This service covers the “oldest” Websites, now named as Web Apps, the Azure Mobile Services, now, Mobile Apps, and introduce new capabilities as Logic Apps and the API Apps. This article talks about the last one.
The question is: What’s the reason to create an API App, and not a Web API in a Website? This question can be easily answered, analysing the feature list, for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access Control using Azure Active Directory or OAuth services, as Facebook or Twitter;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fast integration with the Swagger Framework;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy integration with Logic Apps;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Private gallery of APIs, enabling us to provide APIs to the other members of the organization;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automatic generation of an SDK for our API.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article we will see, how to create an API, publish in our subscription and create an SDK to consume it.&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2015 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2015-06-17T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I had the pleasure of write an &lt;a href="http://www.revista-programar.info/artigos/criar-uma-api-no-azure-app-sevice/"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; to the &lt;a href="http://www.revista-programar.info/anuncios/revista-programar-no-49-junho-2015/"&gt;Revista PROGRAMAR&lt;/a&gt;, a Portuguese collaborative magazine about programming. I’m glad with my first article for a magazine and especially because, I'm side by side with people that I admire like &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/PauloMorgado"&gt;Paulo Morgado&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/saramgsilva"&gt;Sara Silva&lt;/a&gt;, for instance. This was an amazing experience and I want to share with you the result of it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March, Microsoft announced an improvement in his services by introducing the new Azure App Service. This service covers the “oldest” Websites, now named as Web Apps, the Azure Mobile Services, now, Mobile Apps, and introduce new capabilities as Logic Apps and the API Apps. This article talks about the last one.
The question is: What’s the reason to create an API App, and not a Web API in a Website? This question can be easily answered, analysing the feature list, for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access Control using Azure Active Directory or OAuth services, as Facebook or Twitter;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fast integration with the Swagger Framework;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy integration with Logic Apps;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Private gallery of APIs, enabling us to provide APIs to the other members of the organization;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automatic generation of an SDK for our API.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article we will see, how to create an API, publish in our subscription and create an SDK to consume it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many services, inside the organizations, that are necessary to multiple applications. A good example of that is the send email notifications.
Let imagine that we pretend to provide an API, so that all applications of our organization, can easily send emails, without need to know the logic of using the email server.
Before we start, we need to be sure that &lt;a href="http://go.microsoft.com/fwlink/?linkid=324322&amp;amp;clcid=0x409"&gt;Microsoft Azure SDK for .NET 2.6&lt;/a&gt; is installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Create an API App project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start to see how to create a project for our API App.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open Visual Studio 2013;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a new project using &lt;strong&gt;File &gt; New Project&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose the template &lt;strong&gt;ASP.NET Web Application&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Give a name to the project, in this case we will use MailApi;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/create-an-api-in-azure-app-service-revista-programar-n49-1.png" alt="New Project" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;strong&gt;OK&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Select the template &lt;strong&gt;Azure API App&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/create-an-api-in-azure-app-service-revista-programar-n49-2.png" alt="Template" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;strong&gt;OK&lt;/strong&gt; and to create the project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Create the service to send emails&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see how to expose a method for sending emails in our API. For that, we will create a class that represents the data model to receive the request, and a controller to provide the sending method. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the folder Models, add a new class with the name MailModel. Mouse right click in the folder Models, and select the option &lt;strong&gt;Add &gt; Class&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the created file, MailModel.cs, add the following code:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

 &lt;pre&gt;
   &lt;code&gt;
    using System.ComponentModel.DataAnnotations;
    public class MailModel
    {
       [Required]
       [EmailAddress]
       public string To { get; set; }

       [Required]
       public string Subject { get; set; }

       [Required]
       public string Body { get; set; }
    }
    &lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add a controller to the project (controllers file) with the name MailController, using the template, &lt;strong&gt;Web API 2 Controller – Empty&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/create-an-api-in-azure-app-service-revista-programar-n49-3.png" alt="Scaffold" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the created file, &lt;strong&gt;MailController.cs&lt;/strong&gt;, add the following method:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

 &lt;pre&gt;
   &lt;code&gt;
    using MailApi.Models;
    [HttpPost]
    public HttpResponseMessage Post([FromBody]MailModel data)
    {
       using (var client = new System.Net.Mail.SmtpClient())
       {
         // create the message
         var mailFrom = new System.Net.Mail.MailAddress("noreply@deathstar.com", "Death Star");
         var mailTo = new System.Net.Mail.MailAddress(data.To);
         var mail = new System.Net.Mail.MailMessage(mailFrom, mailTo);

         mail.Subject = data.Subject;
         mail.Body = data.Body;
         mail.IsBodyHtml = true;

         // send email
         client.Send(mail);
       }
       return Request.CreateResponse(HttpStatusCode.OK);
    }
    &lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Configure the service&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since in this example we will send the e-mail via SMTP, we will need to configure the e-mail server data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access the &lt;strong&gt;Web.config&lt;/strong&gt; file of our application;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the following configuration (before the line &amp;lt;/configuration&amp;gt;):&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

 &lt;pre&gt;
    &lt;code&gt; 
       &amp;lt;system.net&amp;gt;
         &amp;lt;mailSettings&amp;gt;
           &amp;lt;smtp from=&amp;quot;noreply@deathstar.com&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
            &amp;lt;network host=&amp;quot;mail.deathstar.com&amp;quot; port=&amp;quot;587&amp;quot; userName=&amp;quot;noreply@deathstar.com&amp;quot; password=&amp;quot;#MayTheForceBeWithThisPassword!&amp;quot; enableSsl=&amp;quot;true&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
           &amp;lt;/smtp&amp;gt;
         &amp;lt;/mailSettings&amp;gt;
       &amp;lt;/system.net&amp;gt;
     &lt;/code&gt;
 &lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fill in with the data from our server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Publish the application to the Azure App Service&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The publication can be made to an App Service, previously created using the portal, but in the next step we will see how to create the same without leaving Visual Studio. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this, it’s required to have an Azure subscription. If you don’t have it, you can create one test subscription of a month, in http://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/pricing/free-trial/.
If you already have it, follow the next steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Solution Explorer, right click in project and click &lt;strong&gt;Publish&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the publish dialog, access the &lt;strong&gt;Profile&lt;/strong&gt; panel and choose the option &lt;strong&gt;Microsoft Azure API Apps&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/create-an-api-in-azure-app-service-revista-programar-n49-4.png" alt="Publish" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;strong&gt;New&lt;/strong&gt; to create a new API App in the subscription;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/create-an-api-in-azure-app-service-revista-programar-n49-5.png" alt="Azure API Apps" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the Create dialog, add:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The API App name. Here we will use &lt;strong&gt;MailApiService&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select the disired subscription;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick a name to the App Service;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick a name to the Resource Group;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose the access level Available to Anyone;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick the region where you what to host the App Service.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/create-an-api-in-azure-app-service-revista-programar-n49-6.png" alt="Create API App dialog" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;strong&gt;OK&lt;/strong&gt; and wait a few minutes while the service is being created. The creation request can be followed in the Azure App Service Activity panel;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once the App Service is created, we go back to the step number 1, access the publish dialog, and we click in the &lt;strong&gt;Publish&lt;/strong&gt; option;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/create-an-api-in-azure-app-service-revista-programar-n49-7.png" alt="Publish" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The service will be published.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Consume na API from a .NET client.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see how to create an SDK to our API and use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add a Console Application to our solution;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/create-an-api-in-azure-app-service-revista-programar-n49-8.png" alt="Add console app" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the Solution Explorer, right click in the Console Application and select the option &lt;strong&gt;Add &gt; Azure API App Client&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the presented dialog, pick the option &lt;strong&gt;Download from Microsoft Azure API App&lt;/strong&gt; and select the MailApiService, create previously;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/create-an-api-in-azure-app-service-revista-programar-n49-7.png" alt="Add Azure API App Client" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;strong&gt;OK&lt;/strong&gt; and wait until the SDK is created;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the last step is completed, we are ready to invoke our API, as the following code shows. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
  &lt;code&gt;
  class Program
  {
    static void Main(string[] args)
    {
      var client = new MailApiService();
      var data = new Models.MailModel { To = "darth.vader@deathstar.com", Subject = "War Report", Body = "The Force awakens" };

      var response = client.Mail.Post(data);

      Console.WriteLine("Done!");
      Console.ReadKey();
    }
  }
&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this new service created by Microsoft, we are able to provide features that in the past had a huge development cost, in an easy and quick way. 
The private gallery in conjunction with the easy way to consume APIs, provides the required capabilities to create an API ecosystem. &lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2015/05/lessons-learned-from-agilept-2015/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2015/05/lessons-learned-from-agilept-2015/</link><title>Lessons learned from Agile Portugal 2015</title><description>&lt;p&gt;In the last week I attended to the &lt;a href="http://2015.agilept.org/"&gt;Agile Portugal 2015&lt;/a&gt;, an amazing event that gathers the agile community.
I had the opportunity to listen excellent speakers as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://au.linkedin.com/pub/lachlan-heasman/1/920/777"&gt;Lachlan Heasman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/haradakiro"&gt;Kiro Harada&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/_pedro_torres"&gt;Pedro Gustavo Torres&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.uvu.edu/profpages/profiles/show/user_id/1923"&gt;Neil Harrison&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/theplastictoy"&gt;Ricardo Fiel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/carlton858"&gt;Carlton Nettleton&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event was amazing, and I want to share with you the main lessons that I learned. &lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2015 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2015-05-27T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the last week I attended to the &lt;a href="http://2015.agilept.org/"&gt;Agile Portugal 2015&lt;/a&gt;, an amazing event that gathers the agile community.
I had the opportunity to listen excellent speakers as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://au.linkedin.com/pub/lachlan-heasman/1/920/777"&gt;Lachlan Heasman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/haradakiro"&gt;Kiro Harada&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/_pedro_torres"&gt;Pedro Gustavo Torres&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.uvu.edu/profpages/profiles/show/user_id/1923"&gt;Neil Harrison&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/theplastictoy"&gt;Ricardo Fiel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/carlton858"&gt;Carlton Nettleton&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event was amazing, and I want to share with you the main lessons that I learned. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The importance of Visuals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lachlan Heasman has made an amazing talk. He reinforces that the Visual Management is really important to succeed.&lt;br /&gt;
That thought made a lot of sense to me. Nowadays, we have a ton of excellent applications to do kanban boards and that's OK, especially if you have remote workers. But I believe that, if you have your team in a single place you should have a physical kanban board.
Why? Because your team will look into it every day... every single day. Even if they don't want, they will! You will see that your team will be positively influenced, building a culture of transparency and trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/lessons-learned-from-agilept-2015-kanban-style.jpg" alt="Kanban style" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;User stories&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why we are writing User Stories in the form of "As a... I want to... so that..."? Will the customer realize the language? Or will they think that we are crazy nerds?
As the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User_story"&gt;wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; (that eternal font of true) refers, an "user story is a description consisting of one or more sentences in the everyday or business language of the end user or user of a system".
Have you ever listened a business person talking like that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carlton Nettleton, presented a simpler and much objective way to write user stories. How? Answering the following questions: Who? What? And Why?
I'm a fan of the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Five_Ws"&gt;Six W's method&lt;/a&gt; to describe and understand complex problems, and Carlton made me correlate that with user stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The true essence of agile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The industry sells us the idea that Agile (or Scrum), is a magic formula that we should apply to have good results. You just need to have some meetings, do sprints of "X" weeks and you will be fine. 
That's not true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies are made from people, so they are different. Each one has a different culture and a different identity. This uniqueness will make them agile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agile, isn't a process, a system or a mathematical formula. Agile is a culture. 
It's different be agile than have a certificate that says that you are agile.
The process is the less important part. You should have the focus on the outcome. 
Always think on where you want to go, not on what you need to do to go there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was an amazing day, with incredible people, in an awesome place. 
Hope to be there next year.&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2015/05/azure-app-service-api-apps-microsoft-rest-httpoperationexception/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2015/05/azure-app-service-api-apps-microsoft-rest-httpoperationexception/</link><title>Azure App Service API Apps - Microsoft.Rest.HttpOperationException</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I was playing with API Apps, from the new Azure App Service when I faced the following error:&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2015 23:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2015-05-11T23:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I was playing with API Apps, from the new Azure App Service when I faced the following error:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
    Microsoft.Rest.HttpOperationException`1 was unhandled
  HResult=-2146233088
  Message=Exception of type 'Microsoft.Rest.HttpOperationException`1[System.Object]' was thrown.
  Source=MyMailSenderClient2
  StackTrace:
       at MyMailSenderClient2.Mail.&lt;PostWithOperationResponseAsync&gt;d__0.MoveNext() in c:\DEV\MyTestApi\MyMailSenderClient2\TestMailApi\Mail.cs:line 129
    --- End of stack trace from previous location where exception was thrown ---
       at System.Runtime.CompilerServices.TaskAwaiter.ThrowForNonSuccess(Task task)
       at System.Runtime.CompilerServices.TaskAwaiter.HandleNonSuccessAndDebuggerNotification(Task task)
       at System.Runtime.CompilerServices.ConfiguredTaskAwaitable`1.ConfiguredTaskAwaiter.GetResult()
       at MyMailSenderClient2.MailExtensions.&lt;PostAsync&gt;d__3.MoveNext() in c:\DEV\MyTestApi\MyMailSenderClient2\TestMailApi\MailExtensions.cs:line 42
    --- End of stack trace from previous location where exception was thrown ---
       at System.Runtime.CompilerServices.TaskAwaiter.ThrowForNonSuccess(Task task)
       at System.Runtime.CompilerServices.TaskAwaiter.HandleNonSuccessAndDebuggerNotification(Task task)
       at System.Runtime.CompilerServices.TaskAwaiter`1.GetResult()
       at MyMailSenderClient2.MailExtensions.Post(IMail operations, MailModel data) in c:\DEV\MyTestApi\MyMailSenderClient2\TestMailApi\MailExtensions.cs:line 24
       at MyMailSenderClient2.Program.Main(String[] args) in c:\DEV\MyTestApi\MyMailSenderClient2\Program.cs:line 16
       at System.AppDomain._nExecuteAssembly(RuntimeAssembly assembly, String[] args)
       at System.AppDomain.ExecuteAssembly(String assemblyFile, Evidence assemblySecurity, String[] args)
       at Microsoft.VisualStudio.HostingProcess.HostProc.RunUsersAssembly()
       at System.Threading.ThreadHelper.ThreadStart_Context(Object state)
       at System.Threading.ExecutionContext.RunInternal(ExecutionContext executionContext, ContextCallback callback, Object state, Boolean preserveSyncCtx)
       at System.Threading.ExecutionContext.Run(ExecutionContext executionContext, ContextCallback callback, Object state, Boolean preserveSyncCtx)
       at System.Threading.ExecutionContext.Run(ExecutionContext executionContext, ContextCallback callback, Object state)
       at System.Threading.ThreadHelper.ThreadStart()
  InnerException: 

&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I struggled a bit until I figured why. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, let me explain you how I got there and what I have done to solve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I access to the new &lt;a href="http://portal.azure.com"&gt;Portal&lt;/a&gt; and I created a new API App, then I've followed the Microsoft tutorial of how to &lt;a href="http://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/documentation/articles/app-service-dotnet-create-api-app/"&gt;Create an ASP.NET API app in Azure App Service&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything was going fine and in a few minutes I published the API. Quick and easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, I generated my Client SDK and when I tried to invoke it, I got the error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the exception message and the stack trace don't provide much information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to struggle a bit to figure it out. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason was really simple, my API service had the Access Level defined as &lt;strong&gt;Internal&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After changing it to &lt;strong&gt;Public (anonymous)&lt;/strong&gt; everything works fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/azure-app-service-api-apps-microsoft-rest-httpoperationexception-access-level.png" alt="Azure API App - Access Level" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why this happened? If you follow the tutorial you will create the API App using Visual Studio and you will see that the Visual Studio has the access level &lt;strong&gt;Available to Anyone&lt;/strong&gt; as default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you create the API App using the portal, you will see that the Access Level is defined as &lt;strong&gt;Internal&lt;/strong&gt; by default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that Microsoft will fix these small problems and make it more clear.
Until then, I hope that this helps you.&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2015/03/angularjs-after-render-directive/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2015/03/angularjs-after-render-directive/</link><title>AngularJS - After Render Directive</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Do you ever wanted to execute code after your Angular template is completely rendered?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the answer of how you can accomplish that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This a simple tip, but I believe that can be really useful.&lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2015 00:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2015-03-28T00:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Do you ever wanted to execute code after your Angular template is completely rendered?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the answer of how you can accomplish that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This a simple tip, but I believe that can be really useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add the following directive to your application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;myApp.directive('afterRender', ['$timeout', function ($timeout) {
    var def = {
        restrict: 'A',
        terminal: true,
        transclude: false,
        link: function (scope, element, attrs) {
            $timeout(scope.$eval(attrs.afterRender), 0);  //Calling a scoped method
        }
    };
    return def;
}]);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, add the &lt;em&gt;after-render&lt;/em&gt; directive to an element in your template:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;div after-render="missionCompled"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, your application will run the &lt;em&gt;missionCompled&lt;/em&gt; function (or other that you want) in your controller, after the div is rendered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see the working demo on &lt;a href="https://jsfiddle.net/gsferreira/h53okjtu/"&gt;JSFiddle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that this helps you.&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gsferreira.com/archive/2015/03/a-developers-thoughts-on-azure-sql-database-performance-levels/</guid><link>http://gsferreira.com/archive/2015/03/a-developers-thoughts-on-azure-sql-database-performance-levels/</link><title>A developer's thoughts on Azure SQL Database performance levels</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I recently started moving some databases that I have in the old Azure SQL Database Web/Business model. I started it with a good feeling. Let's face it, a guaranteed performance level is excellent. Nobody wants a noisy neighbor boring our database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The downside, is that this shift brings new challenges and possible big troubles to the ones that already have systems in place. Everything has a price and in this case we call it &lt;strong&gt;Performance&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

</description><pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2015 00:00:00 Z</pubDate><a10:updated>2015-03-14T00:00:00Z</a10:updated><a10:content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently started moving some databases that I have in the old Azure SQL Database Web/Business model. I started it with a good feeling. Let's face it, a guaranteed performance level is excellent. Nobody wants a noisy neighbor boring our database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The downside, is that this shift brings new challenges and possible big troubles to the ones that already have systems in place. Everything has a price and in this case we call it &lt;strong&gt;Performance&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this new model, SQL Azure Databases are paid by performance instead of space. Now we have service tiers with transaction rates per hour (Basic Tier), per minute (Standard Tier) or per second (Premium Tier).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what's wrong with this? The prices! In my opinion, there's no equality between the old models and the new ones. Chris Bailiss has some awesome posts that shows that. Take a look:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://cbailiss.wordpress.com/2015/01/31/azure-sql-database-v12-ga-performance-inc-cpu-benchmaring/"&gt;Azure SQL Database: v12 GA Performance inc. CPU Benchmaring&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://cbailiss.wordpress.com/2014/09/16/performance-in-new-azure-sql-database-performance-tiers/"&gt;GA Performance in New Azure SQL Database Performance Tiers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Show me the numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have an Azure SQL Database on the Web model with 1.5GB you will pay 10.42€/month.
By a few more cents (11.18€/month) you can use an SQL Database in the Standard Tier with the S0 Performance Level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have read the Chris Bailiss post, you have seen that the performance between those two can't be compared. S0 is slower than Web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;So, what can I do?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this post &lt;strong&gt;I don't want to say that you should run away from SQL Azure Database&lt;/strong&gt;. What I mean, is that the game has changed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this Cloud era the costs are a variable that Software Developers and Architects need to take in account. Now our code has a visible and measurable impact in the financial health of our products and companies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how to start facing the dragon?
You can find here a list of things that you should have in mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question yourself: Do I really need a SQL database?&lt;/strong&gt; There's many options in Azure to store your data, probably they can do the task.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Performance is more important than ever!&lt;/strong&gt; Don't wait until a query takes a few minutes running to start doing SQL Tuning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Database design has a significant importance!&lt;/strong&gt; Be careful designing your database data model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Test in Azure since the first day.&lt;/strong&gt; Probably your development machine has an SQL Server with more power than the production database.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gsferreira.com/images/a-developers-thoughts-on-azure-sql-database-performance-levels-works-fine-in-dev.jpg" alt="Works fine in Dev" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reduce the "chatty"&lt;/strong&gt; operations in your application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be careful using Entity Framework.&lt;/strong&gt; Make sure that your code isn't triggering multiple queries that can be done at once. EF can make your life easier, but the database can suffer from that. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start using cache.&lt;/strong&gt; This will reduce the workload at your database and you will consume less DTUs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope this helps.&lt;/p&gt;
</a10:content></item></channel></rss>